<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Powers to be resisted, or, A dialogue argving the Parliaments lawfull resistance of the powers now in armes against them and that archbishops, bishops, curates, mueters, all these are to be cut off by the law of God, therefore to be cast out by the law of the land ... : also an answere to this quere, how</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55591</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12090949</idno>
  <idno type="VID">53875</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240954394</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3111</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9420</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12090949</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53875)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 241:E79, no 15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Powers to be resisted, or, A dialogue argving the Parliaments lawfull resistance of the powers now in armes against them and that archbishops, bishops, curates, mueters, all these are to be cut off by the law of God, therefore to be cast out by the law of the land ... : also an answere to this quere, how</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 60, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Overton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Ferne, H. --  (Henry), 1602-1662. --  Conscience satisfied.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Lauren Proux </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53875:1"/>
            <p>Powers to be Resisted: OR A DIALOGUE ARGVING The Parliaments lawfull Resistance of the Powers now in Armes against them; And that Archbishops, Bishops, Curates, Neuters, all these are to be cut off by the Law of God; Therefore to be cast out by the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>Very necessary and usefull for the information of the ignorant, confirmation of the weake, stablishing of the strong, convincing of the froward, in the clearing, resolving, and stating the legality of the Covenant, and this present Warre.</p>
            <p>Also an Answere to this Quere, How farre Religion may be defended by the Law of Armes? being a thing much questioned by some.</p>
            <p>Here is also a fit Answere to D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> FERNS late Answer, such as God hath commanded to be given unto him, who (in the Title and Close of his book) hath exalted his Folly, and his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse before the face of all the Christian world.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Isa. 5.23.</hi>
                  </bibl> Woe unto them that justifie the wicked, and take away the righteousnesse of the righteous from them.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Psal. 69.19.</hi>
                  </bibl> Thou hast knowne my reproach, my shame and my dishonour, mine adversaries are all before Thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 14.14.</hi>
                  </bibl> The Lord shall fight for you, and you shall hold your peace</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Overton</hi> in Popes-head-Alley, 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:53875:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53875:2"/>
            <head>POWERS TO BE RESISTED. Or a Dialogue arguing the PARLIA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS lawfull resistance of the Powers now in Armes against them.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  <hi>Am very unresolved in point of resisting the powers.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Distinguish of <hi>Powers,</hi> and you may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved, please you: There are <hi>Powers</hi> appointed for the good of man, his safeguard and protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: There are <hi>Powers</hi> pointed directly to the hurt of man, his spoyling and destruction: <hi>Powers</hi> of light, for God is light▪ <hi>Powers</hi> of darknesse; and <hi>Powers</hi> also within a man ruling in darknesse, <hi>self-will,</hi> and <hi>carnall reason.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But,</hi> there is no power but of God; the powers that are, are<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2.</note> ordained of God. <hi>Therefore no resisting, as it follows.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>It is sacred Scripture, therefore a sacred Truth; no <hi>Power,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Supr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me or Subordinate, but is of God; appointed by God; for what? To <hi>bee a terror to evill workes,</hi> and workers: A comfort and encouragement to <hi>good workes</hi> and good men. But there are Powers not Supreme nor sub-ordinate, that are as contrary to all this, as evill is to good, (which, in a large sence, may be said to bee of <hi>God</hi> too) pointed as aforesaid▪ to destroy man, made in the Image of God. These are <hi>principalities</hi> and <hi>powers,</hi> and Devills they are. Powers also there are within a man, <hi>self-will</hi> and <hi>carnall reason,</hi> very evill <hi>Spirits</hi> also, serving to execute the Divells pleasure, whereof we shall heare more anon, and the clearest proofe, That these must be resisted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You are in the Clouds already, and above them, too high for me▪ If you would have men understand you, you must speake low and plaine words, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53875:3"/> may be felt, heard, and understood. This is it, wherein I would be fully, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and clearly resolved: Where the</hi> Law <hi>is, which seales your Warrant to resist the King?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed I would not have had you have mentioned the King; But since you have done it, we will make as honourable mention of the King as we can; and turne off all the envy to another thing, that <hi>Lords</hi>-it over the King and would <hi>Lord</hi>-it over his people too (which shall never be) and <hi>hinc ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e lachrim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> hence all our sorrows. But before I passe on, I must stand still and wonder. A wonderfull thing! that you will never bee satisfied; Is there not answer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter answer unto that, which clears the lawfullnesse of our resistance, as the noone day?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No, yee never yeelded so far, nor granted yee hitherto, That yee resisted the King, though you be up in Armes</hi> against him, <hi>Say I.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>For him,</hi> say we; for we will never yeeld, that <hi>wee resist the King:</hi> we will maintaine a lawfull resistance, which God blesseth: and abhor the contrary, which God curseth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What Resistance is that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>A resistance of a <hi>private will,</hi> active enough of its self, but made more active being stirred up by that <hi>evill Spirit,</hi> which rules mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the world now a dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I smell out your distinction now, you distinguish betwixt what the King does as Lord over us; and what his</hi> will <hi>does, as Lord over him.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, for there is a wide difference betwixt what a King does by Law: and what his <hi>Will</hi> does without, or against Law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I will hold to this still,</hi> The King can doe no wrong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>And I to this still; That <hi>selfe-will, carnall Reason,</hi> (call it what you will, an evill Spirit it is) has done wrong, does doe wrong, and will do all the mischiefe it <hi>Can</hi> doe, while it is its <hi>selfe,</hi> and rules in a man; This <hi>will,</hi> this <hi>Carnall reason,</hi> saies one<note n="(a)" place="margin">Bernard Oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. Ser. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> was <hi>the Serpent in the Garden,</hi> and so he goes on, telling us what <hi>Carnall will</hi> has done, throughout the sacred Chronicle: and we could carry on the Story throughout our Chronicles all up to, <hi>as it does at this day.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, let</hi> will <hi>doe what it will doe, we allow no resistance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No resistance man! You forget your selfe sure, you do hold That your owne <hi>will</hi> and <hi>Carnall reason</hi> is to be resisted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No indeed not I.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No indeed not you! Then you doe, what you have a <hi>will</hi> to doe, what Carnall reason dictates to be done, and then you are a very Rebell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.5.</note> you doe <hi>evill with both hands,</hi> as <hi>you can;</hi> so choaking Conscience as you may. Remember your self, man, and you will yeeld presently, that there is a wide difference betwixt what you doe, and what you ought to doe, and that you ought to resist your own <hi>will.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53875:3"/>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No, I ought not, I thinke, for I suppose, that</hi> will <hi>is the chiefe and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame faculty in man; and why ought not [to doe as the highest Commands mee?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Will</hi> is indeed supreme in you, for it <hi>will</hi> be so; It is a Rebell, an Usurper, and that will perch above its betters, and controule them. But you must know, that the <hi>understanding</hi> is the supreme fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, though the <hi>will</hi> can <hi>over-power</hi> it (because That faculty also has lost its dignity:) I say, the <hi>will</hi> over-rules the understanding many times, (but that argueth the impotence of the <hi>will</hi>) for when the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding has resolved the case, and the best way, in giving sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as supreme; then the <hi>will</hi> can resolve against it, and follow a crosse way, according to its owne determination, after the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, has given its verdict; and so in a short time <hi>will</hi> can put out the light in the understanding, set up for a guide there, as in a watch Tower, and choake the mouth of Conscience quite. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thus I argue; You ought to resist your greatest enemy, that you have upon the Earth, or in the Aire (where evill Spirits are) or in the bottomlesse-pit, where their <hi>King</hi> is: But <hi>self-will</hi> or Carnall Reason is the greatest Enemy of any you have in any of these quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Earth, Aire, or Hell, therefore <hi>selfe will</hi> is to be resisted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I know whereto you drive now; That a man, being himselfe, Cast into the lap of his owne will, let alone to guide his owne steps, to hold his owne r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ines, that such a man is</hi> the greatest enemy to himself.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Yes indeed is he, and as certainly so, as twice three is six: It were an easier Judgment for a man to bee delivered-up to <hi>Satan,</hi> the Devill, That <hi>Adversary,</hi> then to be delivered-up to his owne <hi>Will,</hi> to bee let alone to walke in his <hi>owne way;</hi> the former may tend to the <hi>destruction of the flesh;</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</note> the latter tends directly to the destruction of the soule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, and what if I grant so much, and that I am he, the greatest ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to my selfe, what then? who has to doe with that? and wbat if I grant too, that I must resist</hi> my selfe, <hi>my carnall reason, it does not follow that therefore the King is to be resisted.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>No, I argue not for that resistance, against it rather, but it followes, <hi>selfe-will</hi> is to be resisted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, so it does not relate to the King.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>So it does not relate to the King! you will be medling still, and so make the case more cleare against you: <hi>Selfe-will</hi> is rather, and more to be resisted in a King then in a private person: for in a private person, though it be the greatest enemy he has, yet it may hurt but himselfe onely: but <hi>selfe-will</hi> in a King is indeed his owne greatest enemy, but being <hi>let alone</hi> and not resisted, may destroy <hi>three kingdomes:</hi> Therefore <hi>selfe-will</hi> commanding in a King is more and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53875:4"/> rather to be resisted then in another man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, I say againe, and will stand to it, let</hi> Selfe-will <hi>be King in a King, and let it doe what it</hi> will <hi>doe, Ile allow no resistance, no kinde of resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, none at all.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Now you have spoken out, and wisely you thinke, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you speake foolishly; You will allow no resistance, non at all! It is but your will, you have no reason for it at all no not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reason; you have not choaked that yet; does not your reason tell you. that <hi>the devill is to be resisted?</hi> Remember your selfe, man, you doe hold it lawfull <hi>to resist the divel,</hi> doe you not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, now I remember my selfe, I doe hold that resistance lawfull, though I resist him not; and if I should hold the contrary, you would hold that the divel were in me, he held and possessed me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I should hold so indeed; but from what you grant, I inferre, <hi>That it is lawfull t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> resist a private will, where ever it commands, but more especially in publike persons,</hi> as are a King and Queene Regent: That which is private in private persons, is publike in them, so publike person:s and so the rather to be resisted by publike persons; I mean those, who are to see unto it, that <hi>Law</hi> governs and not <hi>Will.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That I deny now, your inference I meane.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I shall prove it; but let us understand first what <hi>Selfe-will</hi> is. It is nothing else but the <hi>Manager</hi> of the Divels and his Bishops af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires here on earth; their <hi>agent</hi> and <hi>factour</hi> it is here in the world; so it hath been in all ages, so it is at this day: The Divel cast the Saints into prison once; so he doth now: It was not the Divel then in person, nor is it he now: The divel did it then by the managers of his wrath, his evill servants, and so he does the very same now: he does cast the Saints into prison now, into the fire and water now, yet not he in propriety of speech, but the <hi>Manager</hi> of his wrath, <hi>selfe-will,</hi> egged-on by an evill spirit, so potent in the world as aforesaid: The devill delights in proud wrath, and so he did from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and time was when with his owne hands (as I may say) he exercised the same wrath, when he made poore creatures, men, and women, and children (the object of his wrath ever; for when hee destroyed the <hi>Gadarens Swine,</hi> it was with an intention to destroy the <hi>Gadarens;</hi> to grieve them so, that they might, in a discontent with their losse, throw away their blessing, bid their <hi>Lord God</hi> depart from them, and out of their coasts; when (I say) he made poore creatures) cruell and terrible, and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rce upon themselves; and when he cast the servants of the Lord, as he did the child into the fire, and into the water; all this he hath done with his owne hands. Now the divel works more secretly, cunningly, and wilily, (for we know his <hi>wiles</hi> and his depths;) he works by his agent now; he workes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53875:4"/> and wins upon the <hi>Will</hi> mightily, gaines that, engageth that to be his ready servant, as his eldest Son, the <hi>first borne of his strength,</hi> and <hi>right-hand</hi> now in the world; and having done so, he doth his work with ease. Then, when the <hi>Will</hi> is gained, when that becomes a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy minister of Sathan; what then?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21.</note> then out-comes all that was in the heart; then that shop (sinke, hell rather) is opened, and out comes <hi>Murthers, Adulteries, blasphemies:</hi> Then <hi>Protestations</hi> are made, and <hi>Declarations</hi> shew themselves, and <hi>Proclamations</hi> issue forth, and <hi>Commissions</hi> are sealed (to warrant, I will not say what▪ but what the Divel wills) and a <hi>Pacification</hi> concluded; with whom? with the Divels eldest Sons, the very right-hands of the time; so all is done now to the Divels heart; as he would have it, so all is done, for he hath gained the <hi>Will.</hi> As it is when God has gained the <hi>Will</hi> (which he gained by <hi>speaking</hi> to it with a <hi>strong hand,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Isa.</hi> 8.11.</note> for it is a <hi>stiffe</hi> and stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne thing, as hardly turned backe in its way, as <hi>Jordan</hi> in its course; but when it is turned backe and gained) then the <hi>Will</hi> is presently Gods ready Minister, as the Angels are; it stands before the LORD, having its eares boared, wide open, and with its loines readie girt, to receive and doe according as its LORDS instructions and commands are, either for doing or suffering his Lords good will and pleasure: I say it againe, that it may be well observed, When the <hi>Will</hi> is turned by that Almighty hand, when it is gained by a <hi>creating Word</hi> from his mouth, then the <hi>Will</hi> sayes as <hi>Paul</hi> did. <hi>LORD, what wilt thou have me to doe?</hi> Doe but speake <hi>Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 9.6.</note> if it be thy will that I shall goe through fire and water, I will goe; If it be thy command, and I know it to be thy command, I will not dispute, I will obey: I will not complaine, <hi>There is a Lyon in the way,</hi> while I am in my <hi>Lords</hi> way; nor will I aske any other que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion but this, <hi>LORD, what wilt thou have me to doe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus it is with a man when God has gained his <hi>Will;</hi> and just so it is with a man when the Devill has gained his <hi>Will,</hi> the man is as ready a <hi>minister</hi> for the Devills service, his eares are boared, as wide open, and his loines are as ready girt to receive, and doe the Devils commands; without a complement, the man sayes to the Divell, <hi>Your servant, Sir;</hi> nay, <hi>Your Gregory▪ your thrice-humble Servant;</hi> Lord what wilt thou have me to do? I am at your beck, a nod is enough to signifie your pleasure; no sooner you have given an intimation thereof but it shall be done; a peace shall be concluded with the Irish monsters. Whence this readinesse? How comes it to passe, that a man, made in Gods image, is become now <hi>Servus ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorum,</hi> a slave? how so? The Devill has gained his Will. Now we understand what <hi>Selfe-will</hi> is, and whose Servant it is, and what service it does in the world, and how ready and nimble it is upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53875:5"/> the Divells work; what the Divell motions and commands to bee done, it does, and it does it <hi>suddenly,</hi> being the Divells ready servant and right hand in the World.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I deny still, that</hi> selfe will <hi>is the Devills Servant.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>You may deny that the Divell is a Divell, or that <hi>Satan</hi> is, as his name is an <hi>Adversary,</hi> that there is any evill in the heart, or poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in the Serpent; All this you may deny as reasonably as what you doe deny. But deny what you will deny, This is as well clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Truth, as any that shines in the World; That <hi>selfe will</hi> is the Divels greatest <hi>Centurion</hi> in the World, no such servant as <hi>selfe will▪</hi> It Commands for the Divell, and to answer his pleasure, as <hi>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> love</hi> in the soul Commands for GOD: It Commands eyes, and eares, and hands, and feet, and all, come and they come, goe and they goe, doe this and that for the Divells service, and it does it: <hi>Will</hi> while it its <hi>selfe,</hi> and Regent in a man, is the Divells greatest <hi>Centurion</hi> upon Earth, it cannot reasonably be denyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You will have your saying, and what then? what if</hi> Selfe will <hi>will be the Devils Servant, what then?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>Then we must resist it, for if we must resist the Master, then the Servant sure, all law and reason in the World for that; If I must not suffer the Lord and Master to cut my Throat, I must not suffer his Servants sure to murther me; I must resist <hi>Will</hi> the Devils sl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve: And which must not bee omitted; This resistance argueth the purest obedience, loyalty, duty and good service to the person, whose <hi>Will</hi> is resisted, that is Conceivable: so I have done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I have not done, I am where I was, and where I will bee, for this</hi> I <hi>affirme still; That if the King</hi> wills <hi>the impoverishing Cities, laying waste Townes, if his pleasure be, that his licenced Souldiers (Skilfull to destroy) shall have a</hi> Commission <hi>to doe what they have a</hi> will <hi>to doe,</hi> Plunder Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. <hi>&amp;c. yet my opinion is, there ought to bee no Resistance at all; and my honest Mr.</hi> Ferne <hi>holds fast my opinion too.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>B.</speaker>
               <p>I thought how we should issue the point, for I know Dr. <hi>Ferne</hi> is your Master; and that folly will not depart from a foole, who thinks himself wiser then seven men, that can give a Reason. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding I will try another Argument with you; and <hi>bray the foole</hi> anon a little more, to put him off from his opinion if it can be.</p>
            </sp>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53875:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>ARGUMENT II.</hi> It is lawfull to take a Sword out of a mad Mans hand, Is it not?</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, for if I should deny that, you would say I were mad too; but what then?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Then it is lawfull to resist the Sword in an Adversaries hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is no cleare Consequence; you are to pray for your Enemy, and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary▪ I thinke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, if he bee sober, or any hope by prayer to make him so; But if he be mad, ready to pluck out your Throat, if a double mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse be in him, then you must resist him with all your power, must you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, if he be so mad; and had you said so at first, you had not been inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, but now you must prove the Enemy and Adversary to be mad.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>That I argue thus; If the Enemy and Adversary does now in the cleare light and Sunshine of the Gospel against the Righteous,<note place="margin">He is exceeding wicked, who doe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> wickednes with a light in his hand.</note> the same which <hi>Saul</hi> did in the dark and night of his ignorance, then the enemy is as <hi>Saul</hi> was, mad with rage: But the Adversarie does now in the light and sunshine of the Gospel, against the Kings best Subjects, the same that <hi>Saul</hi> did in the night of his ignorance against the Righteous; Therefore the Adversary is now, as <hi>Saul</hi> was then, <hi>mad with rage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I know not what you meane by this Adversary.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not to the purpose, but this is to the purpose, That <hi>hee</hi> is <hi>mad with rage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If you meane the King, I am resolved to grant nothing. I will not grant that the King is an adversary and Enemy, nor mad with rage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor will I affirme it for a world; I will not speake against my Conscience. I cannot thinke That the King (as King) Can be an Enemy and Adversary to his Kingdome. But this I doe affirm, That the Adversary and enemy is mad▪ starke mad with rage, dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly mad▪ mad upon his Idols, and mad with rage; therefore wee must resist him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It rests in you to prove now, That the Adversary and enemy is mad with rage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>That is proved already, The enemy does as Saul did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am as wise as I was before; I know not whom you meane, whether</hi> Saul <hi>the King, or</hi> Saul <hi>afterwards called</hi> Paul.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Take whom you will you cannot bee mistaken. They were both persecutors, only with this difference, th'one persecuted David (<hi>i. e.</hi> the faithfull of the Lord) in the darke night of his ignorance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53875:6"/> so God was gracious unto him, and he repented, but this Saul, while a persecutor, was <hi>mad with rage,</hi> and so hee saies of himself, when hee came to himself. The enemy does now as Saul did then, <hi>breathing out threatnings, &amp;c.</hi> therefore he is mad with rage His thoughts say as much,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 9.1. &amp; 26.11.</note> made legible by his hand in the bloodiest Characters; his words are as Sauls were, hee <hi>breaths out threatnings</hi> (I speake of him single, though he is plurall, a legion, for he is many) he threatens to slaughter the righteous; so he breaths forth threatnings, and slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters against the <hi>Disciples</hi> of <hi>the Lord,</hi> as Saul did when hee was mad with rage.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He persecutes the righteous as far as his hand will reach; hee makes havock of them; God, Angels and men are Witnesses, that so the Adversary and enemy does: and in the clearest light he does this, against all the laws of Heaven, and the clearest laws of all the Kingdomes on earth: Saul did so in the darke; but hee had a Law by which he did it too, yet when he came to himself and was sober, he acknowledgeth he was <hi>exceedingly</hi> mad with rage. The Adversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie does, this against all law, except the law of his own will, mad against the godly; Therefore it is lawfull to wrest the sword out of the Adversaries hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Surely you meane the King all this while; Therefore I will recall all that was said and deny all.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not meane the King; True it is, and let the King look to that, God chargeth all upon him, which he Commands, or suffers to be done: But I utterly deny that the King can do all as aforesaid, as <hi>King;</hi> he is King by that power, which God hath intrusted him with, and in reference thereunto, to bee obeyed: and therefore, as <hi>King</hi> over a free people, he cannot <hi>enslav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> his people, and destroy his Kingdome. I meane all this while the Enemy and Adversary, him, that has done all as abovesaid, and is starke mad with rage, and mad upon his Idols, therefore to be resisted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why? bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> To deale with you in your owne Argument; though Saul did doe as indeed hee did, breath out threatnings and slaughters, yet the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples then did not wrest the Sword out of his hand, they committed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto God, and suffered patiently.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>True, and there is good Reason for that, hinted before. For though <hi>Saul</hi> did what he did in the dark and night of his ignorance, yet hee did it by a Law in force then, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccording to order; hee had letters from the high Priest, which gave him Commission to enter into every house, and <hi>hale-men and women out thence,</hi> and <hi>commit them to prison,</hi> hee did make havock of the Church, hee cast abroad the rage of his wrath, but by virtue of the <hi>high Priests Warrant,</hi> which stood in force at that time: That, which the Adversary does now,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53875:6"/> is in the clearest light, by warrant from the Pope their <hi>high Priest</hi> whom we stand bound to withstand, or by virtue of his own war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and commission, which his owne will has framed against the clearest light from heaven, and the clearest Law and Reason upon earth: It is most cleare, That the <hi>Adversary</hi> and <hi>Enemy</hi> are doubly mad, <hi>mad upon their idols,</hi> and <hi>mad with rage;</hi> therefore it is not onely lawfull, but the greatest service that can bee done to them, or any one of them, to the private and common-wealth, To wrest the sword out of their hand, which is so destructive to the King and kingdome there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if there be a</hi> Kingly power <hi>with or in the Adversaries and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hand, they must be obeyed as well when they are mad with rage, as when they are sober with reason.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I have done: for though I know what to say more, yet more needs not; it is a mad mans objection, and he will receive no an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere: yet if I would contend any longer, I would deny that a <hi>Kingly power</hi> (for by that I understand a <hi>lawfull power</hi>) can bee put-over into an adversaries hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I speake the words of truth and sobernesse, ye are subjects, ye ought not to resist.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>We are <hi>subjects,</hi> not <hi>slaves;</hi> free-men, not Servants to the lusts and will of man: the Church has but one <hi>Leader,</hi> and he is their <hi>Commander;</hi> they stand charged to obey no other, but as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands from Gods mouth; nor to follow any other, but as he leads unto Him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who shall be Iudge of this</hi> Commander <hi>and this</hi> Leading?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Not the Pope, nor his Church, but <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Word;</hi> and I hope you are content to stand to that <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ipirage.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ever their umpirage is, I will hold to that I first said, Ye are the Kings subjects, and must subject your selves to him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> he subjects himselfe to God and his Law, no further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The King commands obedience, and will have it.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>God commands obedience, and must have it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I cannot examine the commands, the sword must decide i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, and let power carry it: All the Nations upon the earth are on the Kings side.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, all the <hi>Nations</hi> that are <hi>angry</hi> against our side, because the <hi>Lord Christ has taken to himselfe power</hi> now;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.17.</note> all these are on the Kings side: and also all the sottish, bruitish Pastors and people all over the Christian world: All these are mad with rage, and on the Kings side too, (a mighty Argument to prevaile with every sober-man not to wheele-about turne taile, and joine with that side.) But yet, though such a <hi>multit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> of many people</hi> are on the Kings side, and a <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing of Nations like the rus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing of many waters,</hi> yet there are more on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53875:7"/> the Churches side (the Parliaments side,) for the <hi>Lord</hi> their <hi>God is with them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 23.21, <hi>Isa.</hi> 17.13.</note> and the <hi>shout of a King is amongst them.</hi> He shall <hi>rebuke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>se Nations among them:</hi> he shall chase them as <hi>the chaffe of the mountaines before the winde, and like a rolling thing before the whirlewind.</hi> The Church is assured it shall be so, she is not carefull about it. They do their duty, they ply their work, they know the cause shall be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; some maintaine it with a respect to their honour, some to their profits, the fewest in a pure zeale; but wee rejoice, and must rejoice in this, The cause is maintained, and shall be maintained; The cause must prosper; we know it must. There is a <hi>seeking people,</hi> who seeke not great things on earth, neither honours, nor profits, nor pleasures, nor long life, nor the life of their enemies for a prey, their conversion rather: They seeke, and they will seek, that <hi>Popery,</hi> and <hi>Prelacy</hi> may downe; That their Lord Christs throne may bee exalted: They seeke that the <hi>abomination</hi> of <hi>desolation▪</hi> the Kings Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, may be removed; and yet not so much doe they seeke the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move of that generation of men▪ as that the <hi>accursed things</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved out of the Land, which gives strength thereunto: They <hi>seeke</hi> not so much that the sword may be removed, as that the sinne may be removed, which has brought the sword, and furbished the same.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But what will you say now if the Kings Majesty will be pleased to make a peace with you (as he has with the Irish) what will you say now if God will answere your prayers now, and bring him backe to his Parliament at last, as you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rayed, and prayed, and prayed so oft?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I never prayed for his comming to his Parliament; I prayed, and doe pray, as well as I can, that he may feele it to be an evill, and a bitter thing, That ever he departed from his Parliament, for ever since he has pursued the soules of the righteous, and their blood has pursued him. It is a good prayer for ought I can tell my selfe, <hi>LORD bring the King to his Parliament,</hi> but I could never close with that prayer, because I could not perswade my soule, That it is an <hi>orderly prayer▪</hi> There is betwixt him and the Parliament, I will not say a <hi>gulfe,</hi> such as was betwixt <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Dives,</hi> but I will say there are <hi>depths,</hi> even seas of bloods betwixt the King and his Parliament; And my prayer is, that the King may fall into those deeps that from thence he may cry unto the Lord to pardon the bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sphemies of his.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peace, and consider what you are saying, weigh your words well.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> considered, I have weighed them with all my heart and with all my soul, and I say the blasphemies of his <hi>Protestations, Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, Declarations, Commissions, Pacifications.</hi> 1. He has protested That he stands for God, when he fights against the Almighty with all his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53875:7"/> hands. 2. He has proclaimed warre with the Saints, all the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of the world, the best Subjects to the high God in heaven, and to his Vice-roy on earth. 3. He has declared himselfe for the true Religion with his mouth, and persecuted the true professors thereof with his hand. 4. He has sealed bloody Commissions for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroying a mother-City in Israel, not for her transgression,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psal.</hi> 59.3.</note> nor for her sinne, her Lord knowes: though there is much wickednesse within her, yet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or that but because she stands up for God and His cause above all the Cities in the wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, and is a refuge for the out-casts, she <hi>lets them dw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll with her,</hi> she is <hi>a cover to them from the face <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the spoiler;</hi> and it is her Lords command that so she must doe▪ she must entertaine strangers; But therefore we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e those <hi>Commissions</hi> grant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d for the cutting-off all her helpers within and succours from without. Remember how the wicked have blasphemed thy name, O Lord; And remember this City, O Lord, and all that shee has done for the advancing of Thy Name, and <hi>spare her according to the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tnesse of thy me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cy.</hi> Amen.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. He has made a peace with them who have slaine the servants of the Lord with a rage that reacheth unto heaven: and that these execrable Villaines may doe the like service in England, they are called over hither. The <hi>Lord</hi> bring the man that has done all this into the <hi>deeps</hi> for all this▪ that one deep may call upon another deep; that he may humble <hi>himselfe greatly</hi> before the God of his Fathers, and beseech the Lord his God, <hi>Deliver mee from bloud-guiltinesse,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psal.</hi> 51.14.</note>
                     <hi>O God, thou God of my salvation.</hi> Amen. And when the Lord has heard his prayer from thence, then he comes to his Parliament, and will answere his good peoples expectation, then, and not till then; not till his people has prayed him into the <hi>deeps;</hi> and not till his prayer be heard out of the <hi>deeps:</hi> If the King comes in an orderly way to his Parliament he must passe through these <hi>deep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> he must be deeply humbled▪ he must be a man of sorrowes, he must fall low in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions, his belly must cleave to the dust▪ even to the putting his <hi>mouth there, if there may be hope;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.3.29.</note> All this will be when he is brought backe to his Parliament in a way of mercy to his poore people, and to his owne pretious soule▪ which God grant. Amen▪ Even he Lord grant that the soule of the King may be brought into the deeps for all this, and that the prayer of his soule may be answered from thence, as a poore servants prayer was answered, being in an <hi>agony</hi> and fore combate, thinking her selfe forsaken of the Lord▪ No, not forsaken, for thus shee was answered with very good words and gracious, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> art mine with all thy sinnes: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> and thine with all my Righteousnesse:</hi> such an answere bee to the Lord our King from the Lord. Amen and Amen.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:53875:8"/>2. For the <hi>Peace</hi> (but vvhispered novv, and the last refuge) it is a cursed Peace: Thinke wee that God vvill endure to have his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants spoiled and killed, and &amp;c. and then heare of making a peace vvith him: What Peace▪ God and His people all abominate that peace; such a <hi>Peace,</hi> and such <hi>Peace-makers</hi> are all an abomination to the Lord: let them that seeke peace make peace with their God first, lay hold on His Arme first, stay themselves there-on, and be at peace. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You have not done yet, I doe entreat you before you leave to shew me the war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ant you have to maintaine Religion by the sword.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile shevv you our Warrant, if you vvill shevv us first what Warrant the adversary hath to persecute Religion vvith the svvord▪ to thrust the Lord Christ out of His Throne vvith the svvord; to thrust at the apple of His eye vvith the svvord; to thrust His people from His service vvith the svvord; to destroy a Mother-city in Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael vvith fire and svvord both; shevv us the adversaries Warrant for all this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You may shew it your selves; it is but reading the</hi> Commission <hi>his Majesty sealed to his</hi> right-men, <hi>and good subjects, and sent up to London you know when: Therein is</hi> Warrant <hi>sufficient for doing as aforesaid; it is in full words expressed in the</hi> Commission, This shall be your Warrant to you and every one of you, to destroy a Mother-city in Israel.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>O monstrous! I remember that is the Warrant indeed, and to be abhorred with the soule: It is a Warrant to send a man to the Gallowes, (where hee may bee hanged vvith his pardon about his necke) and from thence to the place of execution, I meane to hell. But since you have dealt so ingenuously vvith me, in shevving me your Warrant, Ile shevv you our Warrant, to defend our persons from the povver of the svvord. The <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> gives us this <hi>Warrant,</hi> To keep the Murtherer from our throats, To get our heads from under the foot of pride if wee can: The Lord God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Mercies gives His poore Servants so much leave as <hi>Nature</hi> gives a poore vvorme, it vvill vvringle avvay from the foot, and <hi>earth</hi> it selfe. And this is the very Warrant that whole <hi>States</hi> have had in severall quarters of the vvorld, to vvrest themselves from-out the hand of violence, and are novv <hi>Free States</hi> at this day, proclaimed free by the Law of Armes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You have said, but not a word to purpose: you tell me Nature allowes to defend your person with the sword; you should answere my question,</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be lavvfull to defend Religion with the sword?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It followes from the <hi>lesse to the greater;</hi> What! does the Lavv of Nations warrant us to defend our persons and states from the hand of violence, and does not the Law of God (not to speake of the <hi>Law
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53875:8"/> of Nations,</hi> for if the law of God bee on our side, we are sure, we have all the Lawes on our side, and does not) That Law warrant us to maintaine the Lawes of God, the Rights of his Kingdome, the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and priviledges of His Subjects; The great Trust of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. To defend all these <hi>with the sword,</hi> against those, who would destroy, overthrow, make void, and null, all the laws of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and of His Kingdomes on the earth; does not the law of <hi>God</hi> give his people this <hi>warrant,</hi> to <hi>strive</hi> about these matters?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, it is expresly said;</hi> The Servants of the Lord must not strive,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                     <hi>must not fight with the sword.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>True, they must be meeke and gentle; they must not fight one with another;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 15 30. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but they must fight the battels of the Lord, <hi>strive toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with me,</hi> saies <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Read on,</hi> in your prayers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It followes indeed, for they are the Churches most prevailing weapons, <hi>prayers</hi> and <hi>teares;</hi> But the Church has another weapon, and that is the <hi>Sword</hi> which her people have not a Law only, but an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to use, <hi>earnestly contend for the faith,</hi> saies <hi>Iude,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iude</hi> 3. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the servant of Jesus Christ.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What man! with the sword?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes man with the sword: if the adversary contends against the <hi>Common-salvation,</hi> against the <hi>Common Trust,</hi> and <hi>faith</hi> of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, then we have our Exhortation, <hi>earnestly to contend</hi> (against this Adversary, with the Sword) <hi>for the faith.</hi> It is lawfull to contend with the sword, that's out of question. I call God, Angels and Men to record upon this now; That if it be lawfull in any case, then in this case, in our case, it is lawfull to Contend with the <hi>Sword</hi> for the <hi>Common salvation,</hi> for the <hi>Faith,</hi> the Common <hi>Trust</hi> of the Kingdome: If in any case lawfull to contend with the sword, then in this Case, I call God, Angels and men to witnesse here. Come, man, let us <hi>shew our sel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es men,</hi> and reason the case a little as reasonable men▪ Do we see a <hi>pearle</hi> (the pearle in the Gospel, is the Gospel, the Common Salvation, the Faith of the Kingdome) doe wee see this trod-under by Swine, Swinish men? Doe wee see this, or doe wee not see it?<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Surely, it must be answered, <hi>we doe see it.</hi> What! and doe wee not thinke it lawfull to Contend for it? To rescue a <hi>Pearle</hi> trod-under now by the feet of Pride, as Mire in the streets? Not lawfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for a pearle (man) against the Swine of the Earth, Swine and Dogs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No not lawfull to contend against them with the Sword.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>How then I pray you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>With prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Contend against Swine and Dogs with Prayer!</hi> I never heard the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53875:9"/> like since I was borne. A vaine thing it is sure▪ To pray the Swine not to trample the pearle under foot: To pray the Dogs not to rent you; The Dogs are flying in your face, and you will pray them to be quiet; implacable Creatures! the more you pray, the more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable they will bee. Let us remember what the Lord affirmes, though he puts it downe in way of Question;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 41.2.</note>
                     <hi>The Leviathan will not make supplications to thee, he will not sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ke soft unto thee.</hi> Surely the Lords Servants may say as much of these <hi>Swine</hi> and <hi>Dogs,</hi> wee may make supplications unto them; wee may speake soft (words) unto them, they will not deale so with us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Surely, you have no logick, if Reason bee logick; as they say it is: You doe not keepe</hi> ad Idem, <hi>what have wee to doe with</hi> Swine <hi>and</hi> Dogs, <hi>man, how fell you upon them?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>They fell upon us, and, and as our case stands, we have to do with none else in the World;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.</note> none else but <hi>Dogs</hi> will turne back, and rent you: None but Swine will trample a <hi>pearle</hi> under foot; it is a most cleared truth, cleared by our Lord Christ hims<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lfe: That wee must Contend with these is granted; with what weapon, that is the question; with the <hi>sword</hi> I say; no, with <hi>Prayers</hi> you say: who is in the right? Judge you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If by</hi> Swine <hi>and</hi> Dogs, <hi>you meane Swinish and bruitish men, I have nothing to reply.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>If I meane swinish and bruitish men! why you cannot mean any other:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth</hi> 7 6. Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y Swine is a wicked man; but every wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man is not a Swine; he only who opposeth Religion, tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples under the <hi>Pearle.</hi>
                     </note> These men only saith the Lord Christ, doe <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>teare</hi> His Servants! and trample their <hi>Pearle</hi> under-foot; And is it not very cleere unto you now, That <hi>Prayers</hi> will not move those kind of men, they must be removed with the <hi>Sw rd?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, very cleare; And</hi> I <hi>thanke you for your paines; surely now, that I kn w, who are</hi> Swine <hi>and</hi> Dogs, <hi>I shall never say againe, that such a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men, must be</hi> resisted with Prayers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I intend your information heartily, and resolved you at first, that I would be as plaine as possibly I could, and speake words that might be felt; but if any light has come into your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, you will praise God for that. We go on now, I will question you a little further▪ Doe you thinke that there are in our dayes any such men, that will <hi>rent</hi> and <hi>teare</hi> those who have the same image with them, and will trample a <hi>pearle</hi> under foot?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thinke, say you;</hi> I <hi>know it as sure as there are</hi> swine <hi>and</hi> dogges <hi>in the land; lions, beares, wolves, in the world, so sure I know there are such a swinish brutish generation of men up in armes in our land. Indeed (Sir)</hi> I <hi>take it not well that you should put such a question unto me: True it is, through Gods good providence over me these</hi> dogges <hi>have not</hi> rent <hi>me, yet</hi> I <hi>am very sensible what they have done in</hi> Ireland, <hi>what in</hi> England, <hi>and what their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:53875:9"/> will and full purpose of heart is to doe: I am able also to consider how impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable they are; and what they doe to the</hi> pearle (<hi>by which you understand</hi> Religion) <hi>is very well knowne unto me; and what they have a will and full purpose of heart to doe, as their chaines shall be lengthened out unto them, and the bridle (upon their chaps, but the reines in Gods hand) shall be let-out: I know all this, as well as I know what fire will doe on the tops of houses, and a devouring flood in the time of harvest, which leaves no food.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, blesse God for what you know, walke humbly before Him, and you shall know more every day; <hi>The Lord teacheth the meeke in his way, makes all light before them,</hi> whereas Hee leaves the proud in the darke, to blunder-on upon the drawne sword. And surely your Master <hi>Ferne</hi> is a great example of all this, which appears by an <hi>Answer</hi> he has lately sent from <hi>Oxford;</hi> you need not be at three Farthings cost to buy it, for the scope and tendency thereof is knowne to all the world; it is to make the King <hi>glad with lyes;</hi> to strengthen the hand of violence; to make the Adversary blunder-on more boldl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gainst the drawne sword in the Angels hand; to make his foot stand more firme in the <hi>path of the destroyer</hi> for a time, and to make him <hi>slide</hi> and fall in due time, and rise no more: This I knew to be the generall intendment of the booke before I saw it; yet I did desire to peruse it better, and for that purpose it was sent unto me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have you read the Doctor so quickly, that you can give judgement of him?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, not as you call a reading, but I have read him as serves my purpose.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray you what are your thoughts of him?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not use to tell my thoughts, till I have well <hi>formed,</hi> and then <hi>weighed</hi> them, that I may speake not what I <hi>thinke,</hi> but what I <hi>know:</hi> I know he contends against God and Religion, with as much <hi>for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ead (i. e.</hi> impudent boldnesse) as a righteous people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for God and his cause with <hi>trembling</hi> and <hi>godly feare:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Quae pro Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione cum gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di metu &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 19</note> It is <hi>Salvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> note of difference betwixt a godly and a wicked man, and it is notable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How come you to know this, and yet have not read the booke?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile answer you for that: I looked upon the FACE (that tells you what is at the heart) of his Book, and then upon the <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tle;</hi> an homely word, but it is the name the <hi>Lord</hi> gives its Author;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Isa.</hi> 9.15.</note>
                     <hi>The Prophet that teacheth lyes, he is the taile;</hi> he speakes lyes, and makes the King <hi>glad with them,</hi> therefore he is the <hi>Taile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You speake by a</hi> figure <hi>sure, and that I understand not; I told you at first you must be plaine, you must stoop to me; I must</hi> feele <hi>your words as a blinde man feeles your hand in the darke; for (walking in ignorance) in the dark I am.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53875:10"/>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Its well you know so much of your <hi>ignorance;</hi> if it be not knowledge it is the first step to it, <hi>To know how ignorant you are,</hi> and then to seeke knowledge as treasure is sought after: I would t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Doctor knew so much. But to answer your request, and that wee may stoop one to another, and feele each others words, I shall tell you now, That my manner is in reading to fixe upon the <hi>Title</hi> or <hi>Front</hi> of a Booke, and well to consider that first; for it is granted, that every Authour does,<note place="margin">Semper respici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum est ad Titulum. <hi>Plin. Ep.</hi>
                     </note> in compiling his booke, keep a due <hi>respect</hi> alwayes to his Title: Then turning from that very quickly, (as you will doe from that your soule loatheth) I fixed upon the <hi>close</hi> of the booke, the very last page, for there you will finde the <hi>sting,</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yes the Orator, (<hi>Pungit Orator</hi> and <hi>Poeta</hi> too) The Authour is smart and quicke in the close, if any where. Now I will tell you what I finde in both these pages, and require your judgment concerning the same.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Front,</hi> thus impudent he is, for thus he saies in effect, and would have us believe (and then he may goe on smoothly) That <hi>Dogges</hi> and <hi>Swine,</hi> (they are not his words, nor does hee allow of them; nor are they our words, they are the words of the Lord Christ, and then no matter for mans allowance) That Dogges and Swine (if there be any in Ireland or England; for he makes a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion) doe onely <hi>pretend</hi> an offence (marke the word) <hi>Prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> an <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> in shew only and semblance (tha'ts implied in the Title:) but in reality and truth these <hi>Dogges</hi> and <hi>Swine intend the defence of their Soveraignes Power and Rights, the established Religion &amp;c.</hi> This you have in the very close of his booke; Hee has a word more, and then a short prayer, with which we can close very heartily, and say as he does,<note place="margin">You shall have a further reply to his words, and heare more of his prayer, that it is a curse.</note>
                     <hi>Amen.</hi> Your judgement now upon two questions, and so you shall answere his booke as much as needeth, and as God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Doe you thinke that Dogges and Swine <hi>pretend</hi> onely to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; <hi>pretend</hi> onely to <hi>rent</hi> and to <hi>teare; pretend</hi> onely to trample the Pearle under feet: doe these good-fellowes make a shew and sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance onely; <hi>pretend</hi> an offence to the King and Kingdome, but <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</hi> truly and indeed To <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>Person</hi> and the <hi>Pearle:</hi> what think you could you think so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes indeed could I if I could thinke that the Divel and his Servants did but</hi> pretend <hi>to offend</hi> Job, <hi>they did</hi> intend <hi>to defend Persons, and hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and cattell, and all: Or if I could thinke that</hi> Noahs <hi>floud was sent from heaven and the deeps below, to lay the dust onely, and not as a plague to punish the wickednesse of men upon earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You have satisfied the question very well, and I verily beleeve all the Christian world are satisfied too touching that matter, That
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53875:10"/> Dogges and Swine (these bruitish men) do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but <hi>petend</hi> a <hi>defenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> they <hi>intend</hi> an <hi>offence,</hi> robbing, spoiling, murthering, destroying all places and persons whereto their rage can reach; and to trample un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Pearle:</hi> This is an <hi>offence</hi> you thinke, and so thinks every so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber man, except onely one man in sight (but he is not sober) Doctor <hi>Ferne.</hi> One question more, and your answer thereunto; which that you may give feelingly, I will make a supposition first, and then propose a question. I will make it your owne case; for indeed God may make it your case you know not how soon: Suppose that these <hi>Dogges</hi> and <hi>Swine</hi> were entring your house, ready to teare you to pieces, and were laying their bloudy hands upon all your <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> there; Doe but suppose it so, the question is, Would you <hi>pretend</hi> a <hi>defence</hi> now, or would you <hi>intend</hi> your defence really and indeed to the utmost of your power? Pray you answere me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Indeed you doe not well to question a poore simple man so: I am simple indeed, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> so very a foole as not to</hi> intend <hi>my defence against</hi> Dogges <hi>and</hi> Swine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe not take it ill I pray you, I intend your information in as sensible a way as I can imagine; and doe assure you that our betters, the Parliament, Nobles, and worthies there are accounted such fooles; for dogges are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lying at their face, and swine are trampling upon their Jewell, their <hi>Pearle;</hi> (I call it theirs, because they owne it, and doe account of it as of a <hi>Pearle</hi>) Swine are trampling upon this <hi>Pearle,</hi> and yet our Nobles and Worthies are said <hi>To take up Armes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is true, all the reason in the world to</hi> take up Armes <hi>against Swine and Dogges:</hi> I <hi>shall never thinke is reasonable to use</hi> supplications <hi>to those beasts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me goe on▪ They are not <hi>allowed</hi> to take up Armes against <hi>Swine</hi> and <hi>Dogges,</hi> for all power is in the Kings hand, he commands three kingdoms alone; and as he commands and refuseth, so it must be; and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>fuseth to grant a <hi>Commission</hi> unto his Parliament <hi>To ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray the Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e power enough to grant themselves a Commission, and to seale unto it when they have done, have they not?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It is too late to question it now; they have taken up Armes, and they are deeply charged for so doing by <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne</hi> (I will not call a Teacher of lyes Doctor any more) with two the most horrid crimes, <hi>Rebelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> and <hi>Blasphemy:</hi> The former crime is (I suppose) dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused through the body of his booke, but the <hi>sting</hi> is in the <hi>Taile▪</hi> the later is in the second lea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, where he belcheth forth this vomit, <hi>The taking up of Armes by the Parliament,</hi> I <hi>doubt not to call a blaspheming of God and the King.</hi> I shall now conclude clean against him in these
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53875:11"/> Propositions, (1) That the Parliament have taken up Arms against Swine and Dogges: (2) That they are Swine and Dogges vvho have charged the Parliament with rebellion for so doing: (3) And that the charge of blasphemy upon them, is indeed a <hi>Blaspheming of God and the King.</hi> As sure as (by the patience of God) I now breath in this aire▪ so sure am I able to cleare all this even to the eye of the Christian world; and then the whole frame and structure of <hi>Fernes</hi> booke is destroied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I <hi>pray you put-out your ability here, and make good your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I shall doe it, though not in that order I have proposed, for that were to alter the frame of my discourse also,<note place="margin">Not continued but dissolved into a <hi>Dialogue,</hi> that the phansic might have more scope to work upon the understanding.</note> which was begun and proceeded-in to this very place, before I heard of the Doctors Reply. The former of these Propositions is cleared alreadie, yet more light I shall give unto it, though it be to hold-up a candle to the Sun: The other two will fall-in collaterallie, and by necessarie deduction, so as you shall say your understanding is fully cleared touching the same. I proceed now in my proposed method. I was saying, that the Parliament taking-up Armes without leave (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Swine and Dogges) are charged with <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>blasphemy.</hi> And now here is a new charge, They are blasphemed as much on the other hand: Rebels before are hypocrites now, <hi>for they have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up Armes in a pretended defence of Religion and liberty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A pretended defence! who sayes so I pray you?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>That seductor, Doctor <hi>Ferne,</hi> in the forehead of his book.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then be is</hi> all forehead, <hi>as</hi> I <hi>think your phrase is, he is an impudent man, past shame and grace both,</hi> I <hi>thinke, what thinke you?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I think the same which all sober men in the world will say of him now, looking on the <hi>Face</hi> and <hi>Taile</hi> of his booke; That hee is a notorious <hi>Foole,</hi> or a <hi>Knave;</hi> most likely-they will say hee is both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is not that too bitter and harsh a censure?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No, it is not a censure; he is the verie <hi>mouth of Satan,</hi> that old Adversarie; he has dealt worse with the Parliament in point of slander and reproach then the Devil dealt with <hi>Job,</hi> Therefore he is like to heare worse anon; in the meane time this may serve to tell the world what he is, a notorious foole to thinke That the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe but <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tend a defence</hi> against Dogges flying in their faces; and against Svvine trampling upon their Jewell; he is a notable foole for saying so.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Doctor is no foole sure, but</hi> I <hi>am confident he does not speake as he thinkes, not write as he meanes; he does not thinke that the Parliament have taken up Armes in a</hi> pretended defence of Religion and Liberties; <hi>the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53875:11"/> Doctor is not such a foole to thinke so.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Then he is a notorious Knave in print, to publish one thing to the whole world in such letters, which he who runs may read it, and to thinke cleane contrarie; everie sober man will account him a notable Knave for that, and so let him passe with an answer, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his folly;</hi> for what-ever he expects hee deserves no other: Surely he has been <hi>brayed</hi> sufficiently, but a foole and his folly are inseparable. Besides, I verily beleeve he that will peruse the top of his booke and the bottome, will not trouble himselfe farther to enquire what is in the middle: So we will shut up his booke for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But where are we? here is a digression sure, as you Schollers use to call it. Truly</hi> I <hi>know not where</hi> I <hi>am,</hi> I <hi>pray you set me in me in my way again.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I doe not thinke I have digressed: You remember your que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion was, <hi>Whether lawfull to maintaine Religion by the sword?</hi> It was argued, That it is lawfull in some case to contend with the sword; and if in any case, then in our case, to contend for a <hi>Pearle:</hi> Not with the <hi>sword</hi> said you, but with <hi>prayers:</hi> with a sword said I, and not with <hi>Prayers,</hi> because we are to contend with Dogs and Swine; there your understanding was cleared (as fully as I could in a little roomth) touching them, and that it was as vaine to contend against them with praiers, as to contend against a Beare with an Oaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straw: At the verie point of time <hi>Fernes Answere</hi> (I am resolved for just reason never to call him Doctor any more) came to my hand, which told us as aforesaid, and in the fourth page assureth us, that 'tis blasphemie, To maintaine any defence at all about the <hi>pearle,</hi> for that the King and his partie are fully resolved to defend it (that is) <hi>To maintain Religion in its purity.</hi> This shall be fully enquired into and resolved anon; for the present, I have shewed you the <hi>face</hi> of this answere, and the <hi>sting</hi> in its taile: You resolved me two questions about it, and so wee cast it away for that time, as an <hi>accursed thing,</hi> not regarding what is in the middle: And so we returne whence we digressed, that we may conclude it lawfull <hi>To defend Religion with the sword.</hi> And let us take notice in passage, how tender the servants of the Lord have been in everie thing that has concerned the <hi>pearle,</hi> Religion, the service of their God; or has had any respect that way: and great reason the servants of the Lord should bee so tender and cautious in that point, because their Lord has reproved Kings for their sakes. 'Tis worthie all observation, That a zealous Priest once would not suffer a <hi>Censer</hi> to be touched with unwashed hands, yet they were the hands of a King: The Priest dealt roundly with the King, and roughly too, hee <hi>withstood him</hi> saies the Text,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 26.18</note> and <hi>thrust</hi> him out of the Temple, and the King of Kings sets, as a speciall
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53875:12"/> note of dishonour upon the fore-head of the King: So a special note of honour upon the head of the Priest, lifting-him-up above his fellowes;<note place="margin">1 Chron. 6.10.</note>
                     <hi>Azariab is he that executed the Priests Office in the Temple.</hi> What did the Priest doe there? As you heard, he <hi>withstood</hi> the King, hee would not suffer him to pollute the Censer; And this is his <hi>Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall</hi> to the worlds end: <hi>And Azariab executed the Priests Office.</hi> And is there but a <hi>Censer</hi> polluted now? Surely more then a <hi>Censer</hi> is polluted now; Nay, in designe to bee taken away; a more precious thing then a Censer a <hi>Pearle:</hi> The Holy Holy Holy things of Christ, and His <hi>Spouse</hi> are polluted now; The Eternall Gospel is upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe to be destroyed now; all the Lawes and Rights of Heaven and Earth are set under foot now. Surely, That man, whether high or low, Noble-man, Knight, Gentleman or poore man, what ever he be, That stands eminently-out now with his Sword in his hand for the maintenance of the cause in defence of the <hi>Pearle.</hi> He is the man, whom God takes speciall notice of▪ as he did of Azarian; <hi>This M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> executes</hi> his <hi>Office</hi> in <hi>the Kingdome which God has commended to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> care.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Forbeare a little, while I tell you what</hi> Doctor Ferne <hi>saith, That the</hi> Pearle <hi>(Religion) is more deare and precious to the King and his Party, than it is to the Parliament and their party, and the</hi> Primate <hi>of</hi> Ireland, <hi>as I beare, is of that mind too.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 8.9.</note>For the first Man he is not worth the naming, <hi>he has rejected the word of the Lord, and what wisdome is in him?</hi> For the other, this is the least that can be said of him, this is he, <hi>that has not executed his office in the Temple;</hi> He has seen a more sacred thing than the <hi>Censer</hi> handled with unwashed hands, and yet he held his peace. The Lord lay it not unto his charge: or rather. The Lord charge it upon his Soul in Mercy unto his Soule, <hi>Amen.</hi> You shall have further satisfaction to what your <hi>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne</hi> saies▪ in due place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am Conscienously scrupled here, as some few others are, and as hee is who was before your</hi> Committees <hi>two daies agoe. We are ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>t.</hi> I <hi>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse, not</hi> knowing the Scriptures; <hi>But it is grievous to us to walke in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd glad we would be to see our way cleare before us: We are cleerely resolved that the King is in a wrong way; his foot stands covered over with blood in the path of the destroyer, that is cleare unto us, and it is as cleare to our Consciences (yet, till you can resolve as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ontrary from Scripture, and cleare</hi> two Scriptures <hi>to us</hi>) That all, who beare Armes against the King are Rebells all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I thinke so too; Nay I know it to be so; All that beare Armes <hi>against the King</hi> are Rebells, all; but we beare Arms for the King, and the Parliament, therefore we are good Subjects all</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>A Riddle to me! I shall never read it: The King protesteth▪
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53875:12"/> That he fights for the King of Heaven, and for all the <hi>Rights, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> of His Parliament on Earth (I mean His Church) Yee say the very same thing; Yee are for the King, yee say; The King is for you, hee sayes: In the meane time your Swords stand pointed one against the other. There is the Riddle; The Lord read it unto you, make it plaine to all the Christian World, and resolve your Soules in <hi>Rebeckahs</hi> question; <hi>why are wee thus?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.22.</note> why is there such a struggling within the Bowels and Wombe of the Kingdom? all for the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> in words: the greatest number against <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> in deed; <hi>Why are we thus?</hi> I pray you enquire heartily of the <hi>Lord</hi> touching this Matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke you heartily for this Counsell, and to reply in a word, we have enquired of the <hi>Lord</hi> touching this matter, and wee have our answer; That our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>King</hi> is very angry; we▪ His People have grieved him to the very heart; Nay, wee have <hi>broken his heart;</hi> (it is His own expression) and hee has not spared, Hee has broken us with breach upon breach, for mighty Reasons, the one is in sight; <hi>we regarded not the works of God nor the operation of His hand;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Psal. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <hi>The Lord</hi> (seemes) now to <hi>destroy His people, and not build them up;</hi> but not for any wrong wee have done against his King upon Earth, our very thoughts are pure touching that matter, so are our prayers: To his King on earth, we have done none hurt, no wrong at all. but all the right that could bee. The Lord is witnesse, the Lord God of Gods is wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nesse, even he▪ That to His King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>earth we have done none hurt, no wrong at all. This is our appeale, the Lord is judge, he will give answer in his owne time, we wait.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I must now intreat your trouble so far, as to enter-in, and lead me forth of this <hi>Maze.</hi> I my selfe, and others of my mind, are cleare at this point, and take it for granted, which Dr. <hi>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne</hi> calls a <hi>blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of God and the King.</hi> That the King is seduced to a subversion of Religion and lawes; we make no (If) there, his actions have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved us, and made all legible, and you have promised <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o make that matter more cleare. Your maine work is now to cleare your selves in point of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> deeply charged upon you by Dr. <hi>Fern:</hi> what Scriptures hee has to beare out his charge. I know not, I believe, by that you have told me out of him, hee is slenderly read in the booke of God: but yet I am of his mind, till I have cleare resolution from you touching two Scriptures. The first will tell you, I thinke, that you have rebelled against the King. The second will assure you. The primitive Christians did not resist. The first Scripture which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve will hold you a while, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>And Israel rebelled against the house of David unto this day.</hi> I take it, you will read your selves Rebels there;<note place="margin">2 Chro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.19.</note>
                     <hi>They Rebelled</hi> saies the Text.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53875:13"/>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You desire only the exposition of these words, <hi>Rebelled, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, The words are cleere,</hi> Rebelled <hi>is rebelled, and</hi> Against <hi>is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, very plaine English, it needs no comment; I desire to know how you will quit your selves of Rebellion charged upon you in that Text.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very easily and well, but your patience I pray you, while we read the Context; The summe of what that containes is this; That <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> a foolish King, who should have come to his people in the <hi>Spirit of meeknesse,</hi> came unto them with a <hi>Rod</hi> in his hand, shewes them the Rod first, flourisheth it in all the peoples sight; then speakes to the people as out of a whrilwind, storm-like, he assureth them, That the <hi>Rod</hi> they now see in his hand, shall be turned into a <hi>Scorpion</hi> shortly. When Israel saw the <hi>Rod,</hi> and heard of <hi>Scorpion,</hi> they, fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly shew their King their backs, and <hi>went every man to their Tents▪</hi> Israel would not endure to bee whipped with Scorpions, and by their Kings hand,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Psal.</hi> 72.2.</note> who stood charged by his Grand-father, <hi>To break in pieces the oppressor: To judge GODS people with righteousnesse; and his poore with Iudgement:</hi> So they rent themselves from their Lord and King, and went their way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Read on, and read the last verse of the Chapter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I will: <hi>And Israel slipt themselves fron under</hi> Rehoboams <hi>hand: They with-drew their necks from under his grievous yoke</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Indeed you read false.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly, I doe not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You doe, for you should read thus,</hi> and Israel REBELLED.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>So it pleased the Translatour (and the sacred tongue is quicke and short) but in propriety of speech▪ and in the judgement of the Learned, it implies but as was said; And had it pleased the Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, he had said as well, and as properly, if he had translated it, <hi>and Israel revolted,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> for so <hi>Libnah</hi> a City of Priests did; they <hi>revolted from their King;</hi> the word is the same, and has the same poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n the right hand; and to their eternall honour it is spoken, in the judgement, of the best learned, That in so revolting; they did well, and that they did their duty: I shall make clearer proofe anon; They left their King when hee left God; <hi>let him rebell,</hi> They would not, their King should not <hi>Compell</hi> them: And yet they rebelled against their King, if you will have it translated as it is in your text, for the word is the same. we are charged to give the fairest and softest interpretation of Israels doings; I will deale so friend-like with <hi>Ferne,</hi> I could make cleare proof, that he has <hi>prevaricated</hi> in the great and high businesse of the Lord Jesus Christ, I say, <hi>prevaricated:</hi> he has made doublings, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and windings in a plain path, after the methods of the crooked Serpent▪ he has perverted the holy wayes of God; he has prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53875:13"/> you would not take it well now, if I should speake what I know, that hee has <hi>Rebelled</hi> against God, and the King. And yet the word implies so much; for it is the same word you have in the Text, yet I give the word a softer interpretation: I say that <hi>Ferne</hi> has <hi>prevaricated,</hi> and no more, though as a Man in the darke, and that has sold himselfe to doe wickedly, he has done infinitely more▪ he has rebelled once, and again, and now the third time, and means to rebell, for ought appeares to the contrary by his <hi>Scribble,</hi> till he be sent to his owne place. But novv I knovv no sober man, vvho holds That Israel, renting from the house of <hi>David, rebelled</hi> against <hi>Davids</hi> God. If the Adversary cannot prove it to bee a <hi>rebellion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, wee are carelesse what he saies touching the Rebellion against man: If the parting from the King, when his foot stands in the <hi>path of the destroyer,</hi> bee in obedience to <hi>Davids</hi> God, according to his <hi>secret</hi> and <hi>revealed</hi> will, we will not trouble our selves, though it be reckoned by the Rebellious, a rebellious walking <hi>against the house of David:</hi> But grant at the last (vvhich vvill never be granted) That <hi>Israel rebelled,</hi> yet vve must remember this, That which may be called <hi>Rebellion</hi> in them, may bee pure obedience in us. There is as wide a difference betwixt vvhat Israel did then, and vvhat vve do novv, as there is a latitude in the <hi>power</hi> of the Kings of <hi>Is<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ael</hi> then, and the Kings of <hi>England</hi> now. The Kings of Israel vvere more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solute Kings, then are the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> they ruled mostly by their <hi>Prerogative</hi> Royall <hi>(i. e.)</hi> by <hi>meere power.</hi> Our Kings ought to rule by the knovvn Lavvs of the Land. VVe have these Lawes to vvarrant our proceedings, <hi>Israel</hi> not so to vvarrant their revolt▪ The Lavv of nature pleaded for them, and vvhat more I cannot quickly tell my self; but it is very notable which wee read,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 11.4.</note>
                     <hi>The Cause was of God:</hi> Indeed the Lord takes the matter upon himselfe, saying; <hi>This is done of me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You have explained the first word, say somthing to the other, for that is necessary, because</hi> for <hi>and</hi> against, <hi>these two words, have raised the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Question, that ever we heard of in the world untill this day.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a great Question indeed, but fully cleared, and easily resolved. Therefore, touching that other word <hi>(against)</hi> I have but a word to say more; If ever any Parliament since there was a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in <hi>England,</hi> did contend for their King, and against the Kings Adversaries, this is the Parliament: I could abundantly cleare this, had I time and space: Nay, it is cleared to every sober man, and for mad men no matter; The witnesse is in Heaven; to Him His servants have appealed; The Lord God of Gods is their witnesse here, and it is enough; though the Adversary writes bookes against them, no matter, their <hi>Record is on high.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53875:14"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My memory is short, helpe it</hi> I <hi>pray you, and recollect into a short sla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> what was last said.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You may now gather-up all that has been▪ said touching this Scripture into two lines: (1) That your Scripture makes no more proofe, <hi>That all Israel rebelled,</hi> then that <hi>Libnab</hi> rebelled: But most cleare it is to him that will see, that <hi>Libnah</hi> did their dutie in revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from him, who rebelled against God. (2) Grant that Israel rebelled, it does not follow that we rebell; for we walke <hi>orderly</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our knowne Lawes, and the King goes cleare against them; We wage warre in defence of the King and Kingdome, the King wageth a warre which is most contrarie to himselfe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to his kingdome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You have considered me hitherto, a poore ignorant creature, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not distinguish betwixt the right hand and the left, in the things of God: and know no more, but that I am ignorant, and therefore cannot discerne the things that differ;</hi> I <hi>pray you (Sir) cannot you give me a rule from those Scriptures you have touched upon</hi> (concerning Israel and Libnahs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt) <hi>whereby</hi> I <hi>may be able infallibly t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> judge of</hi> Rebellion, <hi>so</hi> banded <hi>to and fro; no body will owne Rebellion, and never were there so many Rebels in the world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It is verie true: I read of a people of whom it is written, That <hi>their actions proclaimed them fooles to all the world, but they could not endure to be called fooles.</hi> A spade will endure to be called a spade; but no such Traitour as he, who is so, but will not endure to bee called so: nor any such <hi>Liar</hi> in the vvorld as is he, who will give you the stab if you give him the lie. It is so at this time, There are a people up in Armes against God and the King, but they will not endure to be called Rebels: Let that passe for the present, wee will finde them out anon, and call them Rebels too. I like your moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on well, surely I will endevour to cleare your judgement touching Rebellion, <hi>How you may judge of a rebellion against Davids house;</hi> brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus: Observe narrowly vvith all your eies (you have more then two) whether you see men bearing-up stoutly against God, contending with him as if they had an arme like God, treading-downe His hedges, breaking-over His bounds, casting away His <hi>cords,</hi> saying in effect, <hi>The Lord Christ shall not be Lord over us:</hi> Doe we heare and see these things? doe we heare men speak blasphemies? doe we see men offering violences to all the lawes of heaven and earth? doe we see this, or doe we not? It must needs be answered, <hi>We doe see it:</hi> Then we doe see the clearest Rebellion against <hi>the house of David:</hi> But when I see nothing which I can call a Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on against God, no not any thing done that has any appearance that way. [For to sence my throat against Murtherers; to safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53875:14"/> my house against Robbers; to flye from the rod in a mans hand, (for his mercies are cruelty) specially when he shall threaten to <hi>sting</hi> me with a <hi>scorpion;</hi> to maintaine the <hi>pearle</hi> also, and to pluck it from under the feet of Swine; none of all this has any shew or appearance of Rebellion against God, none at all:] And if not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, then I must not dare to censure it a <hi>Rebellion against Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids house;</hi> for certainly it cannot be a rebellion against <hi>Davids</hi> house, but it must be against God first.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I <hi>pray you cleare this in the two cases before, and then in our case.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I am about it, to cleare this question here so stiffely contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted in the world, and to shew forth <hi>Rebellion</hi> in its scarlet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, I will, according to your desire instance in the case of <hi>Israels people,</hi> and then of <hi>Israels Priests,</hi> and afterwards make our own case verie legible in theirs.</p>
                  <p>In the first case, What have we in sight? A rod flourishing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the peoples eies, and Scorpions threatned, heavie yokes prepared for the necks of Israel, and a little finger menaced to presse and set-on upon the peoples shoulders heavier then the loines of a man; this was in sight on the <hi>Princes</hi> part, who <hi>wanted understanding,</hi> therefore was he also <hi>a great oppressor;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.16.</note> and all this cleare against the command of God, <hi>Thou shalt not oppresse</hi> (no not) <hi>a stranger,</hi> much lesse thy brother; nay, if thou seest an oppressor of Gods people, <hi>Thou shalt breake him to pieces,</hi> that is the charge. What does Israel doe now? They see the yoke is like to pinch, and they slip their neckes out of it, and away they went.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then they rebelled.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God sayes they did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You can never prove that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>His</hi> word <hi>sayes they did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It does not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The interpreter renders it so.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>But without the booke, for that Word will not prove them Rebels against God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take the softest interpretation, it proves that they</hi> revolted <hi>from their King; And if no more at that time, yet tis cleare to all the world, they</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled <hi>against God▪ presently after.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Now you say something, but you can never make it good, That Israel rebelled against God: the context is cleare, that not one (True) Israelite, (that <hi>set his heart to seeke the Lord</hi>) not one true Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite that would rebell against God; they were,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 11.26</note> as they ought to be, exceeding tender at that point: For when they saw what way <hi>Ieroboam</hi> went in, a way of Rebellion against his God, presently
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53875:15"/> they left him, and hastened to Jerusalem, there to worship God as he commanded. I pray observe the Chapter, you will finde everie (True) Israelite fully resolved against Idolatrie, serving of God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne inventions; and this will evidence them to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to God, and then you can never prove that they rebelled against the house of <hi>David.</hi> Their Kings Idolatries and his oppressions, these are in sight, and great Rebellions against God: In the people you observe no more, but, that they were affrighted at the sight of the rod, and hearing of the Scorpions, and so went their way. It is true, here was a judgment which God inflicted upon <hi>Reboboam</hi> the King, and Israel his people, for the sins of both, no question to be made of that; and there is the first case.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let me heare the other explained concerning Israels Priests;</hi> I <hi>hope I may the better judge of rebellion, when I see their cases both together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed if their actions will beare it, the word will: for, as I told you, it is the same in your Text, <hi>they Rebelled,</hi> though the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter was more considerate and cautious here: for the resolving hereof,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.</note> and making cleare to you, <hi>What it is to rebell,</hi> it is necessary to enforme you what their King <hi>Jehoram</hi> was, and what the Priests did. First, and in two words, their King was a <hi>Barrabas,</hi> a <hi>notable murtherer,</hi> and an abominable Idolater; such a King he was, and the reason is given, <hi>he had the daughter of Ahab to wife;</hi> a woman of a masculine spirit, what she had a will to doe she did, like a Tyrant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Was not her husband King?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, but she was Empresse; he wore the Crowne, but shee swayed it; he had the name, but she ruled: there was no use of a King, but onely of his hand and seale; the Queen <hi>decreed unrighteous decrees,</hi> and <hi>prescribed grievousnesse,</hi> and the King sealed unto them: And then the King <hi>made high places;</hi> [you must not thinke he hoisted-them-up with his owne hand, no more then he did with his owne hands <hi>kill his brethren;</hi> Commissions were sealed, and sent to his ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to that purpose;] and (by prescribing grievousnesse) he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Jerusalem <hi>to commit fornications,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.11</note> and <hi>compelled Iudab</hi> (marke that.) And now you have heard what the King was, and what he did, and who were his Counsellours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What did the Priests?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>As their King did, all that were vile and treacherous, <hi>they willingly followed the commandement.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But what did Libnah doe (as you said) a City of Priests, what did they doe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>They <hi>Revolted,</hi> in that place; They <hi>Rebelled,</hi> in yours, as the Translatour renders it; and indeed some doe say plainly, <hi>Libnah re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s day:</hi> So did the Scots foure yeares agoe; so doe we now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53875:15"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That was my request, That you would inform me, give me a</hi> RULE <hi>whereby to judge of this crime.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I have given it you already, Ile repeat it againe; spy-out here (and yet you need not looke so narrowly) is there any Rebellion in sight here against God?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes sure, in sight a great deale; for here are horrible murthers, abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Idolatries: and here the</hi> Crowne <hi>is laid in the Queenes lap, who was daughter of</hi> Ahab; <hi>and a</hi> Commission <hi>sealed to</hi> compell <hi>Iudah to doe as the King and Queen did.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You observe it very well; and that the King walked most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliously against his God. But have you observed any Rebellion in the Priests?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, there is a word implyes so much,</hi> They revolted, <hi>which my Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>statour renders,</hi> They rebelled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but remember your Rule, and enquire, <hi>did they rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, I finde not a syllable that tends that way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you may be cleare in point of Rebellion; If no Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion against God, none at all, but all in obedience to God, and his command, then <hi>no rebellion against Davids house,</hi> I meane against <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam</hi> their King: Tell me (for you shall be Judge) whether is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, <hi>To obey God, or the King?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is fittest to obey both.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very true, if both can be obeied; but if their commands stand at such a distance, as doe stand the two <hi>Poles,</hi> North and South;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 6.16.</note> the Temple of God and Idols, how then, whom will you obey now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> King <hi>of Kings sure, and</hi> Lord <hi>of Lords; I must obey him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 7.</note>
                     <hi>it is a resolved case.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It was the Priests case. (2) Consider, Gods command draws one way, the Kings hales another vvay, vvhich vvay vvill you take?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The way of the</hi> upright <hi>sure, for that is a lightsome path, the path of Gods commandements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It was the Priests case. (3.) The King forsakes God, God forsakes him, then he blundered-on in the darke path, where was no light, would you blunder after him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, for then I must have fallen▪ and have beene in danger never to have risen againe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I say the third time, It was the Priests case, and the Spirit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presseth it so; <hi>And Libnah revolted from under their Kings hand:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.10</note> Why did they so? <hi>Because he had forsaken the Lord God of his Fathers.</hi> Can you judge of Rebellion now? are you cleare at that point?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truely I am, it is most cleare as is the Sun in the firmament, that the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53875:16"/> King rebelled against God; and the Priests, in pure obedience to God,</hi> revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>from him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell me one thing more; could you be content to be called as the good Priests were called, (nay, are called) <hi>rebels against their King?</hi> could you bee content to bee as they, and in their case, so reproved, would you be content?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Content! Yes indeed could I, and more, I could count it my glory; my glory and Crown of rejoycing, to be accounted a Rebell against my King; a Revolter from him, while in Gods account, I am his faithfull and obedient servant. It is the greatest honour unto Priests and people, To be Rebels and Traitors in the Kings account, and the greatest dishonour to be <hi>right</hi> men for his service, pressed Souldiers for his warfare, so long as he Warres against God, and the House of David.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>VVell said, it is your case, for it is the very case of all Gods faithfull Servants in the world; and this case comes now to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered; for we cannot forget our own case.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> you heartily, That you will resolve me here also; Truly I long for resolution, that I may satisfie my own Conscience, and give righteous Iudgment touching Rebellion in our case. My Iudgment is cleared in the other Cases, but I cannot conceive (it is my ignorance perhaps) how you can make our case so cleare, being so different in my apprehension, to both the former Cases: This was Israels Case, They</hi> revolted, <hi>slipt their necks out of the Collers, as you say, and went their way. They shewed their King the</hi> Heele, <hi>they did not kick with the beele; they did fly from the rod and the Scorpion, they did not contend with their King, to pluck the rod out of his hand. And for</hi> Libnah, <hi>they</hi> revolted <hi>from their King; so we read, and no more; we do not read of any</hi> Sword <hi>held-up against their King. Tell me I pray you, how to judge of Rebellion in our Case, and on whose side it is, for Swords are lifted-up on both sides.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>The Resolution hereunto depends very much upon the resol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you touching that you last spake; You see no violence done by Israel, nor no Swords in the Priests hands: You see vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence done by us you thinke, and Swords in our hands; Therefore if it should be denied, That <hi>Israel</hi> or the <hi>Priests</hi> were Rebellious: yet will it be affirmed, That wee are Rebels. But see how you are mista<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken! our Case exceeds both theirs in sight: First, <hi>Rehoboam</hi> shewes the people the rod, and threatens the Scorpions; King <hi>Charles</hi> (for I will speake out) makes his people feele the Scorpions; and his little finger heavier than his fathers loines. His people resist now; whom? They call God to record, They resist the <hi>Scorpions,</hi> not the King: and notwithstanding all this, they doe not rent themselves, nor depart away from the King: but he rents himselfe from his Parliament, he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53875:16"/> departs away from himselfe, and his good people: Yes, and we must adde, though it is a sad addition, he is departed from God too; The Lord knows how farre (departed) from God, and from all the laws of heaven and earth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>You have said, and I doubt not but you know what you say, but let me tell you what Doctor <hi>Ferne</hi> saies touching this matter; this; <q>That ye are desperately fallen from God and the King; but the King keeps close unto God; you <hi>fight against your King for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion you freely enjoy, out of a feare, and jealously</hi> only of a change: And as for your Army, Besides some Troopes of Forreigners, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists, and some bands of unwilling Prest men, It has its chiefe strength from the prevalency of such Sects,</q> as are condemned by the laws of the Land; and so he concludes very gravely and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously (out of the Booke he takes his Sermon) with these words; <hi>A Frantick Religion needs such furious maintenances, as is rebellion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed you doe not well to quote <hi>Ferne,</hi> a stigmatized fellow, <hi>noted</hi> with his own hands, upon his fore-head for a <hi>Foole</hi> and a <hi>Knave</hi> both, and it shall be cleared anon, That he is the <hi>mouth of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> too, and can any sober man regard what that mouth speakes, or be carefull to make answer thereunto? Yet he may have a returne of his words in due place, and the doubt cleared (though none but <hi>Swinish</hi> men make doubt of it) <hi>who doe fight for the King, and for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and who against both;</hi> and <hi>on whose side these Papists are.</hi> Now you expect I should say somthing to the other Case of <hi>Israels Priests:</hi> It is true, we read nothing of a <hi>Sword</hi> there; The Priests <hi>revolted,</hi> and no more; and the King was so wise, as not to send the Sword after them, to <hi>Compell them to blaspheme;</hi> but had the <hi>heads of the Tribes</hi> been associated, and sitting in <hi>Parliament</hi> about this matter; <hi>whether the King had power to Compell his people</hi> as aforesaid: <hi>And had their King deserted his Parliament; and taken to him</hi> 20000. <hi>men, under preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e of a Guard, but with a full intent to fall upon the heads of Israel;</hi> And to reduce <hi>Libnah,</hi> to his and his Queenes obedience; had it beene so, what would have been done then, I cannot tell my selfe▪ but I believe, then there had bin <hi>Swords</hi> drawing on both sides,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>shua</hi> 22. <hi>Iudgdes</hi> 19.</note> as well as in <hi>Ioshuas</hi> time, and in the dayes of the Judges; But this was not Israels case, then, tis ours now. And now I hope I shall be able to resolve your Conscience, and cleare your understanding, so as you shall bee able to judge <hi>on whose side Rebellion is▪</hi> (That is) you shall clearely <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, beare</hi> and <hi>understand,</hi> who are <hi>Swine</hi> and <hi>Dogs;</hi> who trample upon the <hi>Pearle;</hi> who blaspheme God and the King: I cannot doubt but to give the clearest satisfaction here, that can bee desired, because you shall have all the helps, that are desirable, for the clearing your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding at this point; you shall call up all your <hi>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e wits</hi> (your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53875:17"/>
                     <hi>Senses</hi> I meane) every one shall give-in their evidence, to the Truth then you shall unite all five into one faculty, so as you shall clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see and understand, what you doe. And because we resolve to be serious, and to speake as the <hi>Oracles of God,</hi> That the simple Reader may trust us and believe our report: I charge you before the living God, to answer the truth now, and nothing but the Truth, as you have <hi>heard, seene,</hi> and <hi>understood;</hi> So I begin in order, with that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Organ of knowledge, your <hi>eare,</hi> what heare you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Blasphemies from one side,</hi> I <hi>am sure, for I heare Protestations from both, all for God, and to maintaine Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You see now, you have need of your other sences, for you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not judge by the hearing of your eare: what doe you <hi>read?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Proclamations, Declarations, Commissions, and an Act of pacification with the Irish — and English—</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake out man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I want a word whereby to expresse those execrable</hi> —</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>What doe you <hi>see?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Laws, Rights <hi>and</hi> Liberties <hi>of the Subject, trampled under foot; I see Cities impoverished, Townes wasted, Villages fired, Males mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, Females ravished.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Is that all? You <hi>see</hi> somwhat more sure, you remember the Charge, to speake as in the eares of God; what more doe you see?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I see the</hi> Pearle <hi>trampled under foot also.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>By whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By Swine, for none other but</hi> Swinish men <hi>will trample upon a</hi> Pearle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Then there be <hi>Swine</hi> in <hi>England:</hi> but what doe you <hi>smell;</hi> for I told you, you should use all your sences in this Case; what doe you smell?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Exhalat opaca mephytim.</note>
                     <hi>Truly the most hellish savour, the most loathsome stench, that ever was cast abroad in the world, worse then the stinke from a putrified Corpes; and it is the stinke of the Kings Campe, that comes up into our Nostrils. Every mans throat there, is like an open</hi> Sepulchre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>How doe you <hi>Relish,</hi> what you <hi>heare, read</hi> and <hi>smell</hi> from the Kings side?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As the gall of Aspes to my taste.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>What doe you <hi>feele?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I can say little to that, for the murtherers never came within foure miles of my doores, but had I a <hi>sympathy</hi> (as you Schollers call it) of a member, had I a <hi>fellow feeling</hi> of what is felt, my words would be <hi>sighs,</hi> and you would see them pointed with teares: Truly, to tell how sadly these oppressions speake to the hearts of them, that are companions with those, who suffer; and how sorrowfully they speak,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53875:17"/> who are under these oppressions, is impossible, for it is unspeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed you speake feelingly. Now call upon all your five <hi>wits</hi> together, and unite them into one faculty; then tell mee what you understand touching matters now a daies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I stand at a maze: Ah Lord! VVhat contrarieties in things! What contradictions in words! Confusions in deeds! What Blasphemies! What Murthers! What Villanies! What outrages of all sorts and sizes! What bloody — executions! And that you call the <hi>Pearle</hi> (Religion) how doe Swinish men trample upon it, as mire in the streets!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat observation make you of all this? Do you observe, That there are any Dogs and Swine in the Land?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, multitudes, and that they are Swine and Doggs, who affirme the contrary; and in so doing, doe blaspheme God and the King.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you do observe Rebellion in the Land <hi>against David and his house.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I cannot tell what you meane</hi> by David and his House; <hi>what doe you meane by it (Sir?)</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>King</hi> in heaven, and his King on earth, and his People, his <hi>House</hi> and <hi>Houshold</hi> there; doe you observe any Rebellion now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst David and his house?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah Lord! Observe any Rebellion, say you? I observe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing else but Rebellions; Rebellion against the Lord God of Gods; Rebellions against the King of Saints; Rebellions against the Lord our King and Rebellions against the Lords <hi>Annointed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You meane the King, doe you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, though he is the <hi>Lords anointed;</hi> I meane the people of God, made <hi>Kings and Priests to God the Father;</hi> for such annointed people there was, upon the earth, before there were Kings there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>VVell: who is the chiefest in this Rebellion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Ah Lord! You have charged mee to speake as the Oracle of God, as in his eares The truth, according as all my Senses have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to my understanding; and as my understanding has given in their evidence, and now I must answer — Ah Lord!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not afraid, man, let not the terror of a man make thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid; the Lord, not I, Hee chargeth thee to speake as the Oracle of God, and as in the eares of God, speake out man, what you are able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ake good; It is for God and his cause, and to stop the mouth of the slanderer: You speak for the King, his Crowne and Dignity, and for his soul, that it may prosper at last▪ The breaches he has made upon his Crowne, will not be made up with flattering words; nor will the wounds in his soul, be healed with <hi>balm;</hi> nor can his blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53875:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53875:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53875:19"/> be wiped-off vvith a soft cloth, no more then pitch can be wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped off with Wooll: Speake out what you know, who is the chiefe leader in this great trespasse against the Lord?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ah Lord! the King is chiefe in this rebellion against His Lord, David and his house.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Now looke to it, that you can shew your <hi>evidences,</hi> and make good proofe; for there are strong evidences against you, <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strances,</hi> and <hi>Manifest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'s, Declarations,</hi> and <hi>Protestations,</hi> all from the King to undeceive the people, and to give them confident assurance, <hi>That he Intends the advancing of Gods glory in the first place, The defence of Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n in the second place, The kingdomes Rights and the peoples liberties at the last.</hi> You understand all this, doe you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes very well: I have heard, and seene, and read all this; and all this <hi>deceived</hi> the people a very little time, till the Kings hand de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared it selfe cleane crosse to his tongue, and his deeds were <hi>Contra-Remonstrances</hi> to his words: I observe vvhat the Kings <hi>Actions</hi> have beene and are; what is done, not what is spoken: The glorie of God, and the honour of His Name, has been <hi>pretended,</hi> when the most in-glorious things have been <hi>intended</hi> and practised: And so now, the glorie of God was pretended, shewed forth to the eyes of the people, as a <hi>vaile</hi> cast-over the Kings hands, reached out unto the <hi>Antichrist,</hi> the Pope, and his Bishops, to helpe them in their warre against the <hi>Lambe:</hi> The King has chosen, if not (as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did) <hi>Calves</hi> to be his <hi>gods,</hi> (for this is not so visible, if not so) yet hee has chosen such servants as <hi>Ieroboam</hi> did, Antichrists Servants now; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels then (and no better now) to be his Priests;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 11.15</note> he has entertained Irish-Priests, he has taken them into his bosome, bee has done all that was in the power of his hands to doe against the Lord Christ, and His hidden-ones, to helpe Antichrist and all his helpers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But all this is for the defence of the true religion: so the King prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth, and</hi> Ferne <hi>sayes as much, and more.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I have said already, It is of small weight vvhat the King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testeth, and lesse what <hi>Ferne</hi> affirmeth: The King protesteth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the true Religion; An horrible blasphemie! for who are his defendors? whom takes he to him for to defend Religion? None other but Atheisticall Ruffians, notable murtherers, abominable idolaters; likely men to defend Religion! And what Religion is practised by these defenders? but what was practised in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> daies, Queene <hi>Maries</hi> religion; and so the servants of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ord, the true professors of religion are persecuted now, as in Queen <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> daies, yet the King maintaines the true religion! I say again, an horrible blasphemie, such as was never heard from the beginning upward untill this day, That the King intends to maintaine the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53875:19"/> glorie of God, to defend Religion, when he puts forth his hand, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the power in his hand, to dethrone the Lord Christ, <hi>King of Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>;</hi> To trample upon the <hi>Pearle,</hi> to take away the Gospel, the Crowne of his Crowne, and glorie of his land. Thus you have the summe of what the <hi>Senses</hi> have reported to the mind, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult of that the minde has reported to the understanding, whereby to give righteous judgement.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You are (I perceive) willing to touch as lightly upon these matters, as you could: you have made no mention of those thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand thousand soules slaine in Ireland; but there are Declarations and Remonstrances enough touching that Tragedie, and who were the chiefe Actors therein: One act of Rebellion there is, little thought on, or not at all, but it must not be omitted, because I veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perswade my selfe it was the <hi>Source</hi> and <hi>head-spring</hi> from which all the Rebellion of King and people has issued ever since: In a true sense of duty, and zeale for the Kings prosperity, I will goe-up so high as is that head-spring from <hi>whence profanenesse is gone forth into all the land;</hi> The King commanded the profanation of the Lords day, you forget that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, I thought the Bishops were chiefe in that trespasse; and that you would roule that burden upon their heads anon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>So I will, for they were <hi>right-men</hi> for such a purpose; I doubt not but they were his Counsellours, they advised him to make an experiment of his power, make his people know he was King, if so be his command could give <hi>checke</hi> and <hi>mate</hi> to Gods command, then he might rule over men, and doe what he listed. Doubt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>esse the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops plotted and platted that <hi>Garland</hi> of <hi>May-games,</hi> and then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded their Lord and Master to crowne the Lords day with it: The greatest dishonour and mockerie that ever was offered to the Lord Christ, since the Crowne of Thornes was set upon His head: And as the King was counselled, so hee did more presumptuously then any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>then King before him: <hi>For passe over the Isles of Chittim, and see; und send unto Kedar, and consider diligently,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.10, 11.</note>
                     <hi>and see if there be such a thing: Hath a nation changed their gods, which are no gods?</hi> [or the daies dedicated to the honour of those gods?] But a Christian King, and his people by his command, have changed their God, and His glorie: for what? for a thing of naught, lighter then vanitie, a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice-dance for that which doth not profit indeed. Surely the Lord hath smitten His hand at this profanation, so exceeding; for in so doing the King did set his throne above Gods throne; he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded against the command of God. Certainly his throne is shaken for this, and shall never stand steady and be established, till after his heart be shaken for it with godly sorrow: he has (he does) profane
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:53875:20"/> the <hi>Rest</hi> of God, and has commanded so, doubtlesse he shall be rest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse till he be in the deeps for this, as well as for his Idolatry and bloud-shed. Here is now sufficient proofe, That the King is chiefe in Rebellion against God; what thinke you, vvho is chiefe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion against himselfe, his owne Crowne and dignitie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It must needs be answered, himselfe; For if he be chiefe in Rebellion against God, he must needs be the chiefe Adversary against himselfe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It's very true, but yet I would have you make it as plaine to your Readers understanding, as it is plaine to yours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That I cleare thus: he has hearkened to evill Counsellours, and now he has wrested the Scepter out of his owne hand; he has strucke the Crowne from off his owne head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he has throwne downe his owne throne; he has set on fire</hi> Davids house, <hi>though he can have no other ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fit by it, but to smother himselfe in the smoke. Ah Lord!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Sad things indeed: cleare them I pray you yet more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Scepter of this Kingdome also is a right Scepter, a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Righteousnesse: <hi>The King has throwne judgement and justice out of his hands; he threw away his Scepter, and strucke off his Crowne at the same time, and plucked away the supporters of his throne, the two pillars thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.12.20.28 25.5 29.14 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 7.21</note>Indeed it is most true which you say, <hi>The throne is established in righteousnesse;</hi> it is said twice, nay three times, for the thing is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; judgement and justice are like the two pillars, <hi>Iachim</hi> and <hi>Boaz,</hi> salvation and strength to the King and kingdome. These are (to the throne) as were the stayes on either side <hi>Solomons</hi> throne, or the two Lions that stood besides the stayes, and like the twelve Lions which stood upon the ascent to the throne, all and everie whereof made for the <hi>glorie, peace, security, establishment</hi> of the throne; such supporters: And now that these are throwne out of the hand, and violence and oppression (to doe it) are in the hand in stead thereof; now the <hi>Scepter,</hi> the <hi>Crowne,</hi> the <hi>Throne,</hi> must all fall flat to the ground, for the <hi>Supporters</hi> are gone, <hi>Iudgement</hi> and <hi>Iustue.</hi> So now you are able to judge of a rebellion against <hi>Davids</hi> house, and to give cleare proofe, Who are chiefe in that trespasse: I need not put you to prove now,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>v.</hi> 29 12</note>
                     <hi>That all the Kings Servants are wicked,</hi> for the wisest of Kings has said that so it is, when the King himselfe <hi>hearkens unto lyes,</hi> and is <hi>made glad with them:</hi> Nor will I aske you, whether you observe any Rebellion against <hi>Davids</hi> house; all this is so clear to the eye, that I will not trouble you to say more about it: Onely I pray you let me know your judgement in that, wherein the eye is not commonly so cleared; Doe you thinke that there are no other rebells in the kingdome then they, who are the Kings <hi>Right-men,</hi> Irish — and English — helpers and promoters of this rebellion against <hi>Davids</hi> house; are there no more, thinke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:53875:20"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O yes, many more, and I am one of the number.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, an ingenious confession! but you are not the more rebell because you say so: You meane (I suppose) that you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belled against God, you know not hovv often, and you find rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions in your owne heart: Is it not so, and is not that your mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes indeed, I have rebelled against God, and (in so doing) against</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids <hi>house, and the prosperity thereof, and</hi> I <hi>finde rebelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns in my owne heart s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>l still.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Well I verily beleeve you; Rebellions are in you (you are not in a Rebellion;) you hate them, doe you not? you would ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster and subdue them, would you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes indeed, it is my greatest desire, as strong as after the Lord Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Well said indeed; though you put your selfe in, Ile put you out of the number of Rebells: Nay, God has separated you from that rout; take it upon my word he does not account you a Rebell; therefore goe, count againe, and exempt your selfe, and all like you: Doe your senses tell you that there any Rebels in the kingdome, yet professing themselves on Gods side, and for the house of <hi>David:</hi> These are rebels indeed; are there any such?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes many;</hi> I <hi>know not how many Rebels there are, yet professing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves on the Parliaments side; The Parliament Souldiers are not all Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You speake by a figure, you meane more then you speake; you meane, many of them are as bad as the English — and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish — Doe you meane so?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, for I understand by all your discourse hitherto, and by the interpretation of Christs owne words, that men may be exceeding wicked, as true Devils as <hi>Herod</hi> was a Foxe, and yet not as are the Irish — and English — Dogs and Swine, they.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly you say right; but goe on and tell me what you meane when you say, that all in the Parliaments Armies are not all Saints.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, there are Devils in the Parliaments Army, who have given too just cause unto the Adversarie, Doctor <hi>Ferne,</hi> to tell us, <hi>what is that Religion that the Parliament would by such meanes main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fern</hi> shall have a sharp word anon, but tell him now when you meet vvith him▪ that there were but twelve choice men, chosen by Christ himselfe, and <hi>one of them was a Devill▪</hi> There are twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Souldiers on the Parliaments side,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 6.70</note> and suppose there be twelve hundred Devils there, yet this does cast no more dishonour upon the Parliament, that there are so many Divels in their Armies, then it did upon the Lord Christ that there vvas a Divell amongst the twelve: I shall anon prove <hi>Ferne</hi> himselfe to bee a Divell, and a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53875:21"/> Swine (which is the worst Devill) yet shall it be no reproach to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest men, but a glory rather, that a <hi>Divell</hi> and a <hi>Swine</hi> is discovered; And here now, I must informe your selfe, that it had beene a rash Censure in those daies, to have reproached any of the <hi>Eleven,</hi> because one was a Devill; So, nor are you to reproach so much as our <hi>Armies,</hi> much lesse the <hi>Parliament,</hi> because there are so many Devils there; (though indeed, these are a reproach wherever they are) and much lesse must the wickednesse of a few, bee cast as a reproach upon a <hi>Parliament;</hi> you must consider with all Consideration, what the <hi>Parliament</hi> intends by their Armies on the Land, and Navy on the Seas, what <hi>Intend</hi> they by all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Ferne <hi>Answers you, and indeed it is an offence unto me, These in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to wrest the Scepter out of the Kings hands, the Crowne from his Head; To alter Religion; To overthrow the established frame of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vernment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed you doe not deale fairly with me, when I entreat your answer, such as <hi>sense</hi> and <hi>reason</hi> dictate to you, and you answer me by <hi>Ferne,</hi> the <hi>mouth</hi> that speakes blasphemies, the <hi>mouth</hi> of the Divell (as you shall heare presently) yet to give you full satisfaction, I doe assure you, were <hi>Ferne</hi> as neere my elbow, as you are, I would un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to convince him of blasphemy against <hi>God and the King,</hi> in the Judgment of every sober man; nay in his owne Judgement if he dares yeeld it up to the Judgment of God and the Scriptures, which he will never doe. And because he will not nor will he come at me, and I am resolved not to come to him; I will deale with your selfe, requiring of you to tell mee touching this reproach upon the Parliament; What you <hi>see, heare,</hi> and throughly <hi>understand:</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demand of you then, what are the <hi>Actions</hi> of the Parliament?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alas they are too high for me to see into.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>They are not, you can see infinitly higher (to our finit capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) you can see above the moone, above the Sun too; you can see as high as the highest Starre, you cannot tell how high you can see: Then you can see the <hi>actions</hi> of a Parliament; I demand <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> offered any violence to the Kings person?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I heare they have, and from his owne Pen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You cannot tell that, but I pray you, when you are charged to speake your knowledge, as an Oracle, and as from the Oracle of God, doe not tell me what <hi>heare-say</hi> saies, a most notorious lyar: Tell me what you know; have they not made supplications to him three times, Nay, seven times? have they not petitioned him again and againe, and againe. To doe himselfe, and his people right, to build up his house, and Davids house the house of his Kingdom, To judge Gods people with righteousne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, and his poore with judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, have they not done so? They have, God is witnesse, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53875:21"/> their Consciences too, our eyes also. Have they not been as tender even of his Body, of his <hi>Soule</hi> much more, as of the Apple in their owne eye? They have, God is witnesse, and their Consciences too, our eyes also. Have they not gone backward, and backward a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain and again, and the third time, to hide their Kings nakednesse, which would not be hid? They have, God is witnesse, and their Consciences too, and our eyes also. Have they not sought all meanes to fix the Scepter in his hand; To fasten the Crowne on his head; to establish their King in his Throne, by maintaining Judgement and Justice, the Supporters and Pillars of all this; have they not done so? They have, God is witnesse, their Consciences too, our eyes also.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They have not bin tender of the Kings</hi> Prerogative.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that? Too high indeed for you and I to talke of. But this I dare say, The <hi>Prerogative</hi> was never more talked of, nor never lesse understood: Never so strained as of late, therefore never so broken as now, which must needs bee, when there is not a meane betwixt the Kings <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and the Subjects Priviledges, to So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them together. Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> spake little of her <hi>Prerogative;</hi> but never had any Prince a <hi>Prerogative</hi> at more length and more freedome. A blessed Prerogative, which is bounded within Gods limits: and accursed is that from Gods mouth, which will take power beyond Gods allowance, and exerciseth it against GODS Command; but this is above your understanding, perhaps; I will goe on in the exercise of your <hi>senses;</hi> what benefit have the Subjects found from the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Armies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Some of our friends have found very little benefit from some of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Souldiers, for they have beene plundered by them. Indeed some of the Parliament souldiers have committed strange insolencies, against the known Laws, Rights and Liberties of the Subject.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed I am a little angry; you tell me what some have done, and what some have suffered. I have Answered that already. There are some Divels in the Parliaments Army, and they will doe like Divels: but my Question is touching a generall good; what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit hath the Kingdome received from the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Armies?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vnspeakable benefits; they have been as a</hi> wall <hi>about us by Sea, and by Land; by Seas they have shut up the</hi> doores <hi>and</hi> fronteirs <hi>of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that the</hi> beasts of prey <hi>might not breake-in: Indeed our eyes give cleare judgement in that matter. And had not that Thrice noble Generall (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed for his faithfullnesse in guarding Davids house) had not this excellent Lord beene faithfull to God, the King, and the State; Then whereas a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand beasts of prey have thrust-in, and as many instruments of Death, Ten thousand bad thrust-in upon us, as Beasts of Prey into a vineyard, that has
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53875:22"/> neither</hi> wall <hi>nor</hi> ditch, <hi>nor any such fence; and so (for the Land) to the eternall praise of that excellent Earle,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.9.</note> and of those Lords and Knights: [our hearts are towards the Governours of Israel that offered themselves willingly among the people: blesse yee the Lord] In Command and Commission with him; had not these discharged their Care, and faithfullnesse towards <hi>Davids house,</hi> Then had our Cities all been Ruinous heapes, our Townes and Villages had been made Church-yards, scarce large enough to Bury-in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, you doe see your owne preservation in all this, do you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes indeed, though I ascribe all to Gods wing over mee: These Armes have been a means under God, To keep the VVolfe from my doores, The mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers from entring my house.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You doe remember the 12. of <hi>November,</hi> that <hi>Saturday</hi> night, when the Wolves thought to prey upon the Sheepe in <hi>London;</hi> you remember that, and <hi>Gloucester too,</hi> doe you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed, I remember all this, and a great deale more.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>VVell, and you doe remember to draw forth your <hi>soule to the hungry,</hi> specially to those who are a guard about you and your house, night and day, you remember that. But now you see plainely the <hi>Actions</hi> of the Parliament in their Armies (for the Actions and scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terings, of particular men, are not to be put upon the Parliaments reckoning) are faire and specious, I might say, and glorious, for such they are, that have vexed the Adversary to the heart, made them <hi>storme</hi> like the Devill; Nay, they have <hi>stormed</hi> the Devill; and they have beene able to beare up against all his <hi>storming.</hi> But let me crave your judgment in one thing more; Do you thinke, that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their Armies, doe but <hi>pretend</hi> the Defence of the Kingdome, their Rights, Priviledges, and Liberties there? VVhat thinke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thinke! I know, That every sober Man, does heartily and indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the defence of his Liberty: Then sure, that is the intent of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Forces; They doe not</hi> pretend <hi>a defence of the Kingdomes, the defence of their owne Rights and Liberties there, and intend to fight themselves into slavery; no sober men will doe so, I am confident of that.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed so you may bee, That no sober men will do so, And yet there are Nobles, Knights, and Gentlemen (they would bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted so) who contend with both hands,<note place="margin">Nequitiae sordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> imbuta <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilia</hi> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tenti, <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>l. Max. lib.</hi> 3. 5.</note> tooth and naile, to make themselves slaves: But indeed, as you said well▪ these are not <hi>sober</hi> nor <hi>men</hi> neither in the Heathens account, but <hi>Monsters</hi> who will fight themselves into slaverie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yet Sir give me leave, I pray you, for the better ventilating and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowing the Truth, to quote Doctor</hi> Ferne <hi>once more, that we may heare how be makes good his</hi> Assertion, <hi>That the Parliament doe but</hi> pretend <hi>a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53875:22"/> of the subjects liberty, they</hi> intend <hi>to invade it. These are his words;</hi>
                     <q>The Parliaments Armies are continued, and for the maintaining of them, the liberty and property of their fellow subjects is invaded; so that if the question be put, who are those misemployed fellow subjects that these men pretend to fight against? It is plaine [as is the way of the crooked Serpent] they are such as defend their Soveraignes power, and rights, the established Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and government of this Church and State; their owne property and liberty.</q> In a word, such as will not change their Soveraigne, or the established frame of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Then the man prayes heartily, <hi>The God of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and wisedome cast out all counsels, and defeat all designes that are against the restoring of our peace, and the continuance of the rue, reformed Religion.</hi> What will you say to all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing; not a word will I answer to a man that curseth when he thinkes he prayes, (as you shall see <hi>Fernè</hi> has done) not a word to him, that goes against common principles: you remember the old Rule, <hi>Contra negante<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> principia non est disputandum:</hi> there is no arguing with a man who denies that there are any <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine</hi> in the world, (for if there bee none in Ireland, nor England, there are none in the world:) no answer to him who denies, that Wolves are grievous to the Sheepe; and affirmes, that Sheepe are grievous to the Wolves: who denies, that fire will burne; That mad dogs will bite; That Scorpions will sting: we must say nothing to such mad fooles, who will contradict the verdict that all his outward senses, ears, eyes, &amp;c. and all the inward faculties, <hi>Vnderstanding, Reason, Iudgement,</hi> have given-in unto him. What? has the King and his Armies made no invasion upon the Kingdomes <hi>Lawes, Rights, Liberties? Sensus falluntur inepte,</hi> as was said to one, who must not beleeve his eyes; Can mens estates and lives be taken from them, and more barbarously used then so, and yet not their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> invaded? This is like old <hi>Chaucers</hi> tale of a Fryar, whose belly was his god, he would feed upon the sweetest, Mutton, Goose, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53875:23"/> Pig, but a pitifull man! he would have no cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ture killed for him not he. If <hi>Ferne</hi> had not beene <hi>as one</hi> of those <hi>dogs</hi> and <hi>swine,</hi> and <hi>scorpions,</hi> that have so <hi>rent, stung,</hi> and <hi>spoiled</hi> the Kingdome; nay, if he had not beene. I say not, <hi>as,</hi> but <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them</hi> for <hi>he more then lookes on the day of his brother;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Obad.</hi> 11.12.</note> then had he told us, That the Kings Army <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi> the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the Kingdomes <hi>Liberties,</hi> and subjects <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ght,</hi> for his hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e had beene plundred before this, and more; but the Divell will not hurt his good servants, and <hi>Right</hi>-handed men in the world. And now I had done but that I must intreat you to observe with all observation, That <hi>Fernes</hi> words make clear answer to a grand and grave Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion which is this▪ <hi>What is the Religion The King has so often and so solemnly pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ested to maintaine?</hi> It is that Religion, which the Kings <hi>right-men,</hi> his Ministers, and Servants, <hi>Papists, Atheists, Robbers, Murtherers, Irish</hi> —and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l h</hi>—monsters doe defend It is <hi>Fernes</hi> answer, if you observe his words; Now marke his <hi>Prayer,</hi> and you will observe, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>God</hi> over ruled him as he did <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam,</hi> who intended to <hi>blesse</hi> Moab, and to curse <hi>Israel:</hi> but he did contrary, hee cursed <hi>Moab,</hi> and blessed <hi>Israel;</hi> so this <hi>Balaam</hi> has done now; he intended to blesse the King, his Counsels at home, his designes abroad his Armies in Ireland and England▪ and himselfe with the rest, but he has cursed all these and all together, and not blessed them at all. For thus he prayes, <hi>The God of power and wisedome cast out all counsels, and defeat all designes, that are against the rest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our peace, and the continuance of the true Reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> We will joyne with them in the Close saying, <hi>Amen, so be it. So let all Thine enemies be cast out, and perish, O Lord, for their violence against their brother, let shame cover them; let them be cut-off for ever: But let them, that love Thy Israel, be as the Sun when he goeth forth in his might.</hi> Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thanke you, you have cleared two things unto me, one from his words, the other from his Prayer:</hi> (1) <hi>That the true Religion is but</hi> pretended <hi>by the King and his party but</hi> Popery <hi>is</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. (2) <hi>That a wicked mans</hi> Curse <hi>is to be preferred before his</hi> Blessing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:53875:23"/>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>There is a third lesson, which is very pertinent to, and deducible from our last discourse, which I reserve for you to the last. You doe remember you have but the halfe yet, what your <hi>senses</hi> have reported touching the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments defence of <hi>Libertie;</hi> That it is a reall defence, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended and indeed. I tooke the last first, because I am sure the defence of <hi>Liberty</hi> is first in the order of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and of time with us. That the Parliaments intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are the same for the defence of the true Religion, shall be as fully cleared unto you now: And truly I could doe it very quickly in a continued discourse, for it is but clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring unto you the Parliaments <hi>actions</hi> here also, to be faire and well becomming a Parliament; But because this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended defence of Religion is the grand accusation, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thine enemies have reproached, O Lord, wherewith th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y have reproached the footsteps of thine Anointed,</hi> all Thy faithfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the Land; because, I say, it is the great and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous accusation and now we have to doe with the mouth that speakes <hi>blasphemies,</hi> wee must be large at this point. I shall seeme to divert from it sometimes, that we may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit nothing which may helpe to cleare up your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing in this matter, and to stop the mouth of iniquity, that it may be no more a reproch. The blasphemy is but pointed a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Title page, It runnes-out at length thus, through the chiefe part of the Booke, <hi>The Parliament doe but pretend the defence of Religion: they intend faction.</hi>
                     <q>They countenance Sects and Sectaries▪ Anabaptists &amp;c. such as are condemned by the Lawes of the land; These are their strength in their Armies, together with Papists, [O liar!] and their strength in their House▪ [O monstrous!] They enquire after <hi>Truth,</hi> but at the wrong doore: [not of the Archbishops and Bishops; [no Ile warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt you, not of them that have persecuted the Truth.] nay they do but aske, <hi>What is Truth?</hi> as <hi>Pilate</hi> did▪ they doe not meane to stay their answer; they are resolved upon the Question, what they are resolved to doe, they are pretenders to [our Bishops] Religion [Indeed they are not] established by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53875:24"/> the Lawes of the Kingdome. [Indeed it is not] but they intend a religion that was never allowed of in the world, unlesse by such empty fellowes as themselves.</q> There is the accusation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How does he make it good?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay there he leaves us, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r hee is no wiser then the Divell his master, he is but an <hi>Accuser,</hi> this servant of his is no more. But that he is such another, even the same, we will prove presently by the same helps, which formerly we have made use of, and so we enquire touching the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments <hi>Actions</hi> in this great businesse, The <hi>settling of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Settling! <hi>Why Doctor</hi> Ferne <hi>tells you it is not unsettled, it is an established Religion by the Lawes of the Land.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You doe not well to interrupt me with <hi>Fernes</hi> foppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and fooleries: <hi>Religion established by the Lawes of the land!</hi> I tell you it must be established by the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and rule of His Word, or else it will never be established; Besides, you doe unnecessarily trouble me. It is cleared already to all your eyes, That Religion is <hi>offended,</hi> and more, though I will say no more, for I have said enough. We were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring touching the Parliaments <hi>Actions</hi> in this great and transcendent businesse, <hi>the settling of Religion,</hi> what they have done touching that matter: or what doe they, that they are questioned for notable hypocrites, to be <hi>Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> onely to Religion, <hi>Intenders</hi> of faction; what have they done? What doe they? It is a necessary Question, and onely necessary, such as onely requires answer at this point: for if the Adversary must acknowledge, That the Parliaments <hi>Actions</hi> in this businesse have beene, and are faire, well becomming a Parliament, then I will affirme before the face of heaven and earth, That <hi>Ferne</hi> accusing their <hi>intentions,</hi> is a most malignant wretch, a childe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, an enemy to all goodnesse; nay, a Divell, the very mouth of the Devill, as sure as a true Minister of Christ is an Angell of God, and the mouth of God, so sure. And now if it could be, I would summon up <hi>Ferne,</hi> this adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53875:24"/> or the Divell himselfe to come up now and appeare in this case, and in this accusation; and I would adjure him by the <hi>Living God,</hi> who has given life and being to His Creatures, a <hi>Tongue, Reason</hi> and <hi>Iudgement,</hi> to tell us what he has seene (I doe not say what he has heard, though I durst put him upon that evidence) but what hee has seene in the <hi>Actions</hi> of the Parliament touching this matter; and as sure as I breathe, I doe nor say <hi>J live,</hi> none but God saies so, as sure as by His providence over mee, I doe now breathe, so sure I could silence the Divell now as <hi>David</hi> did silence that evill spirit in <hi>Saul</hi> once. But because this cannot be, I will deale with my sober man, and reason out the case with him as fotmerly I have done, requiring of him to tell mee with the same regard to his words, as he, has who knowes he speakes them not so much to man, as in the eares of God, to tell me what he has <hi>seene, heard</hi> and <hi>understood,</hi> touching the Parliaments <hi>Actions</hi> in the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-on this great worke, the <hi>establishing Religion by the Law of God,</hi> and <hi>rule of His Word;</hi> tell me what you have <hi>seene, heard</hi> and <hi>understood?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This, whereunto all my outward and inward faculties of body and soule give me the clearest testimony, that they have inquired of The Lord touching this mattter upon their beds, and in their clossets.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>That's well; if God is to be enquired of (as indeed we ought to ask at his mouth in every busines) then in this businesse; But now you must not say onely but you must prove what you say, because we have to do with a <hi>Dlv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l,</hi> an <hi>Adversary</hi> indeed: how can you tell that they sought God upon their <hi>beds,</hi> and in their <hi>clossets</hi> for this thing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You will not require of mee further then a judgement of charity; for the certainty God knowes, who sees in the darke, and rewards ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly. And yet I must not walke by sense onely, though this my sense tells me, they have commanded</hi> praying and fasting; <hi>they who have commanded this from others, as</hi> Hester <hi>did, will fast and pray too, and not in the Assemblies onely, but upon the bed, and in the closset: so I judge; and this I know, when the adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarie
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53875:25"/> has beene</hi> cursing, <hi>and</hi> blaspheming, <hi>they have been</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>and</hi> praising: <hi>when the Adversary has beene plundring and spoiling like Beasts of prey, they have beene fasting; and all this I have seene, felt, heard, and understood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but you doe understand also. That they enquire about Religion, mainly to finde out The <hi>right way</hi> of Gods worship.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, that is all, if God be worshipped aright, all is right.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>But doe you thinke that the <hi>way</hi> is easily found out?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, for if so, what need seeking to God by prayer and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but when I aske whether an easie way to finde out, my meaning is, Is it not a very intricate and perplexed way, hard and difficult to finde out?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No sure, I thinke, for it is the</hi> Church way, <hi>an</hi> holy way, <hi>straight and direct forward, no by-path, no turnings and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings in it, (ever the</hi> way <hi>of the crooked Serpent) paved out by The Lord Christ himselfe) though the stones and way-markes are somewhat worne out as the figures in a Diall by the storming-ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le and raine) certainly it is more easie to finde out the way, then to walke in it, because it is a</hi> straight <hi>way, and direct, and we are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prone to turne upon the right hand or the left. But now wee are upon this</hi> holy way, <hi>the way of Gods worship, I pray you let mee aske you in passage, what are your thoughts touching the</hi> Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent way?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I thinke this word <hi>Independent</hi> is an unhappy word, and not proper, but I know the <hi>way</hi> is an <hi>holy</hi> way, and they that are for that <hi>way,</hi> understand their way to the City very well: I am confident also they meane no other <hi>way,</hi> but that you were speaking of a <hi>Church way,</hi> an holy <hi>way,</hi> straight and direct, paved out by the Lord Christ himselfe, and trod in by the best servants that ever the Lord Christ had upon the earth: For in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eir desires they follow Christ, and though <hi>hand passibus aquis,</hi> yet not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly would they swerve from their Lords foot-steps, no not a haires breadth. But you have prevented my questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all this while. Doe you thinke <hi>That the Parliament are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53875:25"/> fit and comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tent Iudges of this way of Gods worship?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Truly I thinke yes; there are great Lawyers and great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines there, and these great men are good men too; and why may not they be all fit to judge of this way?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you consider, There is a great darknesse upon the spirits of men, which hides from them the things of God. There is a vaile, as over <hi>Moses,</hi> so over the things of Christ and way of His worship, which all the hands in the world cannot remove. We must grant also, That the way of his worship and service has layne as a path not used, quite neglected and over shadowed by, I know not what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed things, the inventions of men, I am sure, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hidden from the eye these (I know not how) many yeares. Besides, there are many <hi>Offices</hi> belonging to the service and way of Gods worship, and it is a hard and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate businesse to finde out what these <hi>offices</hi> are; who are fit, and what graces required for the <hi>filling-up</hi> of the office, as the word is; so as the officer may make full proofe,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> That he is completely fitted for the full discharge of his Cure or Office. Therefore, under correction, I thinke that the Parliament are not competent Judges of those matters.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now I bethinke my selfe, I must grant so much, for they grant it themselves; They have called together Divines, learned men, from all quarters, to enquire of them concerning this</hi> way. <hi>But now I must put in a word, and tell you what is said touching that matter also; The Parliament has called together men of their owne mindes, as factious as themselves, and have left-out those honest men the Bishops.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>They call God to record upon their soules touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the former part of the accusation, That it is most false; The good (who onely are charged here) had a single eye to Gods glory in their choice. And for the latter part of the accusation it is false too: some Bishops were chosen (though the unfittest men in the world for such a worke, The <hi>settling of Religion,</hi> who have <hi>unsettled it</hi> altogether, whereof in due time) but they came not. One came and sate there till he saw the Assembly would goe on in a <hi>way</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:53875:26"/> crosse to the Bishops way, so away he went his owne way, though so neere the end of his course. And there were <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscopall</hi> men too, more then enough, which have shewne themselves. But all this does prove and set-off the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>Actions</hi> touching this matter, to be as faire and as comely as could be expected or desired. They enquired at Gods mouth: there is the point. Then called an Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines from all quarters of the Kingdome, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire at their mouth. I would aske the Divell now what could they have done more that they have not done? They have made their choice with a single eye for ought ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to the contrary. But if every 12<seg rend="sup">th</seg> man in the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly now were a Divell, yet the Parliament stands clear in the judgment of every sober man. But what a choice have they made? What an Assembly have we? Such an <hi>Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> as is the envy of all the malignant over the Christian world. Such an Assembly which is the <hi>But</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> at which the Divell, his Bishops, and servants all over the world, doe shoot their arrowes, even bitter words. What thinke you of the <hi>Assembly</hi> now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Past all question, if the Divell and all his Bishops and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants doe hate them, do shoot at them all their arrows, as at a But, then they are the</hi> excellent <hi>of all the two Kingdomes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You conclude very well, for as <hi>Davids delight</hi> was with the Saints, the <hi>excellent in the earth:</hi> so is the Devills hatred and envie toward them, a cleare testimony to that <hi>excellencie</hi> in them. But now you doe reserve all due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to other of Gods Ministers, <hi>excellent</hi> men a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>so, for all cannot be of that Assembly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes sure; but I pray you keepe to the businesse in hand: tell me, what have the Assembly</hi> done? <hi>what have they</hi> settled?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed these are sawcie words. What have they <hi>done,</hi> and what have they <hi>settled?</hi> Though this is not to our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinesse neither: yet Ile tell you first, <hi>They have set a day apart to seeke God.</hi> What thinke you of that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was a good beginning, but what is that to me?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that to you! Indeed you should bee chid:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53875:26"/> Is it nothing to you, that they have <hi>sanctified a fast</hi> all together,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezra</hi> 8 21.</note> (what they have done in private I cannot tell) that they might <hi>afflict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves before their God, to seeke of him a right way;</hi> is this nothing to you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, nothing to me, it is for themselves.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>That's true, for themselves, but they are not for themselves; They sanctified a Fast to seeke of the Lord a right way, as for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, so for you and me (for us); yea and for our <hi>little ones too,</hi> and <hi>for all our substance;</hi> doe you marke that? All our good, all our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, all our substance depends upon this seeking a <hi>right way of worship:</hi> Can you tell what they have done now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile tell you: They have done that was never done while there was a Bishop in that Assemblie: nor never would have been done had there been a Bishop there now; They have got up their hearts to God, they are professed <hi>seekers</hi> of Him, and at His mouth; And what have they obtained? <hi>A framablenesse</hi> of Spirit; Spirits framed to, and intent upon their worke: Is this nothing, or is it nothing unto you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>I spake weaklie, yea wickedlie, I will doe so no more. Yet give me leave to aske you, What hath the Assemblie <hi>setled?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not give you leave to speake of <hi>settling</hi> in this unsetled time, which will be yet more unsetled, (it is much that they have found out a way to <hi>settle</hi> and fixe their owne spirits heavenward) till Bishops are rooted out, and their <hi>established Religion</hi> cast out and gone, speake not of <hi>setling</hi> till that be: expect now a continuance of the earth-quake, and blesse God that they are in a <hi>right way</hi> to <hi>settle</hi> all at the last, and wait with patience: We have seene things we looked not for, great and terrible things to the adversaries of the Lord, gratious and glorious to His Friends and Servants, as was the turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g Jordan back. Blesse we God for what we have seen, and we shall see greater things then these, even a <hi>glorious Reformation,</hi> doubt it not. But doe not thinke (though nothing is impossible to the Lord) that <hi>a Nation shall be converted at once,</hi> that all can be done in a day; that matters concerning the <hi>true worship,</hi> so out of frame, can be brought into frame in one moneth: Rejoice, and be exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glad, that there is a <hi>framablenesse</hi> of hearts, and of words, and of actions, towards this <hi>holy way,</hi> that they are all of one lip, and have all one shoulder. I should goe on in this diversion from our maine purpose, but I recall my selfe, and demand of you, for that is to our purpose, <hi>What have been the actions of the Parliament wherefore they are accused, To pretend the defence of Religion, and intend faction?</hi> Tell me, what are their <hi>actions</hi> now in sight, and before the face of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53875:27"/> world? The adversarie has reported as you heard, tell me what you can report, according to your evidence, from what you have seen, felt, heard, and understood?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That their actions are faire, becomming a Parliament, as</hi> white <hi>and</hi> pure <hi>as is the snow in Salmon, for ought</hi> I <hi>can see, heare, or understand to the contrarie: I speak it from my heart, as in Gods eares.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You have said right, for the Parliament considering they were to consult, and to determine <hi>de ardui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> regni,</hi> concerning the high matters of Gods kingdome, the way and rule of His worship, considering this, <hi>they afflicted their soules to seeke of God the right way:</hi> He bad them call an Assembly of Divines, to heare, and consider matters, They did accordingly; His Ministers assembled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and they are <hi>Seekers</hi> too (I meddle not with particular men, or particular actions;) I say the whole <hi>Assembly</hi> are <hi>seekers</hi> for this matter, for flesh and bloud cannot reveale this <hi>way of worship;</hi> They are <hi>Seekers</hi> unto God night and day, that he would lead them, and carry them in His hand to the end of their vvorke. till He has per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected His worke in them, and by them, for His people, Amen. What say you now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I acknowledge most heartily, that the Parliaments actions are faire and lovely, every way becomming a Parliament, they are in sight</hi> shining, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding white as snow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Heare your <hi>Less n</hi> now, and apply your heart to it: When you heare a mans words, that these are as becomes a Christian; you see his actions such also as becomes his profession; his whole deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as <hi>adornes the Gospel;</hi> (you must waigh him wee call man, as you doe gold, with <hi>Allowance,</hi> for he is light upon the ballance) but vvhen you heare and see all this▪ doe not you come in with your <hi>If</hi> now, and with your <hi>But; The actions are good, if the heart were not evill; but the mans heart is rotten, his intentions naught:</hi> As you regard your name, your profession, your honour, doe not doe so: If you deale so with your brother, you deale with him as the Divel has done with <hi>Iob,</hi> and as <hi>Ferne</hi> has dealt with the Parliament; observe your Rule, <hi>You must make the fairest interpretation of your brothers actions,</hi> saies Master <hi>Perkins;</hi> and it is verie notable, Your brother has done thus and thus, verie soule actions, but evermore make the fairest interpretation thereof, thus; <hi>Such and such are his actions; what his intentions were I cannot tell; nor what I might have done, bad I been under his temptations, I cannot tell that neither.</hi> This is a faire interpretation, cast (as a vaile) over a foule action: But now (for I will repeat it againe) are the actions faire, lovelie, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Christian, are they so? And will you say now, that his <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions</hi> are foule, if you doe (you will not say so) but if you doe, I
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:53875:27"/> will say you are a Devill, and that is the sentence I will now passe upon <hi>Ferne.</hi> The actions of the Parliament are faire and lovely, as becomes a Parliament, who feares God, honours their King, loves their countrey; <hi>Ferne</hi> accuseth their <hi>intentions</hi> now: I call God to record now, and all His faithfull Servants in the world, That <hi>Ferne</hi> is a Devill, a Satan, an Adversarie, an accuser of his brethren; he sees their <hi>actions</hi> are faire, yet he saies their <hi>intentions</hi> are foule; he is an accuser of his brethren, he must be cast out, according to his praier, his <hi>Curse</hi> rather: And so I have done with him, and God give him grace to know what he has done. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thanke you heartily, Sir, for your good lesson, I hope I shall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it, and judge no mans heart but my owne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes that you may, you may judge anothers mans heart; when you heare corrupt words still, and see foule actions still, or mostly such, then you may judge the heart to be yet more corrupt and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: when you see a <hi>winking with the eyes,</hi> a <hi>speaking with the feet, a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching with the fingers,</hi> then you may say the heart is naught,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.13, 14.</note>
                     <hi>froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> and <hi>misthiefe</hi> is there, for all this makes a <hi>commentarie</hi> upon the heart, and you may read a <hi>commentary,</hi> may you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes sure, I may read a Commentarie, but there can be no cleare Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary upon so darke a Text as the heart, it is the darkest of any in the world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very true, yet there is a Commentarie plain enough as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said, which gives you a cleare light into that Text; for example, you may read <hi>Fernes</hi> heart legible in Text Letters, that <hi>frowardnesse, mischiefe, malice,</hi> is there, and that he is a verie Devill, and all this you may judge without breach of charitie, for you read it in Text Letters.</p>
                  <p>I will give you now the <hi>Thred</hi> of all our discourse hitherto, that you may wind-it-up together, and see your way in and out: Your judgemet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is cleared in point of defence, <hi>That Religion is to be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the sword;</hi> Israels cases are resolved, and they are quit of rebellion, and so are we also; you can tell your selfe, and make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port from all your senses, who are dogges and swine, who have trampled upon the Pearle, who have rebelled against <hi>Davids</hi> house, and have blasphemed God and the King; and you see clearly with all your eies, that the Parliament doe really and indeed intend the defence of Religion and Libertie; you have your lesson too, and are able to read the darkest Text by its Commentarie, and you can make cleare proofe to all the world, that <hi>Ferne</hi> is a Foole, a Knave, and a Devill: There we left. But I pray you let me aske, <hi>Doe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member all this?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes indeed, verie well, I thanke God and you, you have so
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53875:28"/> cleared it unto me that I cannot forget it; you have taught mee to make use of all my senses, these have put it to my understanding; my understanding hath put it to my memorie, and there it is fast, as under locke and key.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>It is very well, and fit it is to make use of all our <hi>Powers</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward; God has lent them us for that end, To enform us what is the good way, and then to fix our foot in it, and make us stable, it is a stormy time, it will try us what bottom and founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we have, and what constancy of spirit; we see now many tack-about, and take a contrary side, wheele away to the King; because there is preferment in that way (as they call preferment now a daies) The Scholler, if he will be a <hi>right man,</hi> shall be made a Doctor; The Gentleman a Knight, a Knight a Lord, and the Lord an Earle; <hi>A trap, a gin, a snare to catch Woodcocks!</hi> But I pray you make use of your senses still, doe not put out the light, that will come-in through those doores; And remember, what gaine is it to sell ones soule for some preferment, and honour in the world, if it could be had now; what gaine I say, to have the favour of a King, with the dis-favour of the Almighty? What gaine to be a Servant to mens lusts, and a slave to the Devill, slighting the service of God, wherein is perfect freedome? Pray you consider of it, and this with it; That it is the greatest honour now, to be the Kings Traitor; the truest obedience, to be accounted a Rebell against him; and it is the greatest dishonour under the Sun, to be a right man for his service, to stand with his loines ready girt, eares bored to receive and do his Commands; and so now we are quit of rebellion, your judgment is cleared, Is it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes but.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes and but;</hi> Speake out man, are you not satisfied?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No, for me thinkes still,</hi> yee resist the King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>See what you say! We cannot contend with Dogs and Swine, we cannot resist Scorpions, but wee must resist the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for the King sets on the Dogs, and Commands the Scorpion to sting us; and we cannot resist one, but we must resist both; is not that your meaning?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes sure.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Then wee must let the Dogs fly in our faces, and the swine trample upon the Jewell, and the Scorpions sting us to death; we must suffer all this, must we not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, the Primitive Christians did so, they were</hi> Passive <hi>still;</hi> being Reviled we blesse;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12.</note> being persecuted we suffer it. <hi>Look you here! There is the other Scripture, which assureth us, that the Primitive Christians did not Resist.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>True, for how could they resist, they had not any considerable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53875:28"/> strength on their side (which was in sight) and, which was the want indeed, they had not the Law on their side to warrant their strength, and to put it out: If they served God according to His Word (which they would doe,) if they praied, if they walked hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie before Him, (which they did delight to doe,<note place="margin">Humiles sunt, hoc volunt; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmi sunt, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate laetantur, <hi>Salv</hi> 8.</note>) then were they torne in pieces: I cannot expresse how cruellie they were dealt withall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And was not the Law open to them? could they not have recourse thither?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed, all this the adversarie did by the knowne (Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall) Lawes of the kingdome: Indeed sometimes the Lawes were too short to beare-out their wickednesse, but then they could eeke out the Law at their owne pleasure; for when they found not a Law to justifie what they did, they could finde out a Law to doe what they listed. Blessed be God, it is easier with Christians now then in ancient times; the Primitive Christians lived under those, who would be absolute Monarchs, and ruled as they listed; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians now are subjects to Kings who are subjects also to God and His Law, and stand as fully charged by the <hi>Oath</hi> of God to governe his people by law, as his people stand charged to obey by law.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But if the King breake his</hi> Oath, <hi>is that a warrant for the people to breake theirs?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No, they will not breake Oaths, those firme bands; they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver tooke an oath to yeeld-up their throat to Murtherers, nor to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer dogges to rent them, nor swine to trample upon their Jewell; they never tooke an oath to obey the King, farther then he obeies God; they never swore obedience, or themselves slaves to the lusts of men: Gods people know what <hi>power</hi> they must obey, a lawfull power; and what they stand charged to <hi>resist,</hi> a lawlesse power, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-up into the hands of the most violent and bloudie men, dogges, swine and scorpions; these they must resist: If the King now will not shew himself King in the exercise of <hi>Kingly power,</hi> but will give forth his hands to Swine, and Dogges, and Scorpions, the servants of the Lord will draw their hand from him, that they may not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take with him in his sinnes, and in his plagues; Their vowes are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, they have taken the oath of God, that they will approve themselves good subjects to His Kingdome, faithfull Servants to his Church.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At, but subjects must approve themselves good subjects is their King, faithfull servants to him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>So they have done; no such subjects to their King, as those who subject themselves to the law of Christ; none serve their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:53875:29"/> King so faithfullie, as doe they, who do so serve their God: I should tell you a long storie here, but you shall have the marrow of it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Trip. Hist. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> the result therefrom; <hi>Constantius</hi> would feele the <hi>pulse,</hi> and try the <hi>temper</hi> of his <hi>Ministers,</hi> how loyall and faithfull they would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themselves to their only Lord, and his deputed Vice-gerent: And he found some of his <hi>Ministers,</hi> such as were our Bishops all, very <hi>Weather-Cocks,</hi> or <hi>Tide-Boats,</hi> turning with the wind, and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with the streame (which they thought turned;) <hi>Constantius</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving this, discarded them everie one; thrust them from his side, and out of his Court, using these words; <hi>They will never bee faithfull to my Person, who are unfaithfull to their Master</hi> and mine: It is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved Case ever since there was a King upon Earth, <hi>He that Rebels against</hi> God, <hi>and is a Traitor to his Church, was never good King, nor good Subject.</hi> Therefore we conclude, when the King falls away and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells against God, all good Subjects must fall from him, they must revolt from him (else they are not good) as the good Priests did from a Rebellious King,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.</note> who <hi>Compelled</hi> Judah to walke contrary to God, and so to rush-on upon the Sword in the Angels hand, as you may read at large.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is not much to the purpose, and little to my satisfaction; I understand your opinion is, That the Primitive Christians were</hi> Passive, <hi>they obeyed by sufferings (for that is an obedience) but their suffering was</hi> forced, <hi>because they</hi> must: I <hi>take it, That's your opinion; and that, if the Christians had bad strength or</hi> power <hi>one their side, then they had resisted; Is not that your opinion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No, indeed, it is not; you doe not understand me fully, you doe not take all my words, and yet they are but two: I mentioned <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> both; I pray you take them together, so they will doe us good; If you take them severally, you destroy the Truth; <hi>Power</hi> without <hi>Law,</hi> is as King without Reason; <hi>Law</hi> without <hi>Power</hi> is as a King without strength; If you divide these, Ile tell you what I think: that the <hi>Primitive Christians</hi> would not have resisted their <hi>Lords,</hi> if they had had no more but <hi>power</hi> on their side. But this I know, had they had <hi>power</hi> &amp; <hi>law</hi> both (for there is their warrant) on their side they would have resisted; they would not have indured those insolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Those tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dings down by the foot of pride <hi>I</hi> am confident of thats truly there is so much said, and so fully for the clearing of this, that I know not what to say more; To say more, is but to say what has been said, over and over againe, so I have done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nay, I pray you heare me, while I tell you what a learned Divine (for I thinke it is he,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Th. At. Rothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>am.</note>
                     <hi>that has discovered</hi> a den of Thieves) <hi>told mee in reference unto this Scripture;</hi>
                     <q>The Sword saies hee, is one of Gods sore Iudgments, so
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53875:29"/> are <hi>wild Beasts;</hi> God has now a designe upon the whole land, To destroy some, to correct others, and to purifie a third sort as in the fire, The King (some are so bold as to say) as the Viall of Gods wrath: and the Rebels the hands of the King; (some call them <hi>wild Beasts</hi>) grant it to bee so, yet the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their party doe Rebell against God and the King, in making any resistance; for indeed they doe oppose the great designe of God, which is, To punish and correct us for our sins, by the King, the man of his hand, wherewith God will execute the heat of his displeasure against a God provoking people, what doe you say to this?</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I will reply nothing to such a fellow; if it be he that discove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>den of Thieves,</hi> hee fell foule upon the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and told a Kinsman of mine (a man in yeeres, but a child in understanding) That he might take the <hi>Oath of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.23.</note> as the <hi>Sechemites</hi> did take <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision, with references to their private wealth:</hi> So he might lift up his hand, and subscribe his Name with <hi>Ifs</hi> and <hi>Buts,</hi> with reservations and by-respects; So he was assured he might do,<note place="margin">A conscientious man may scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and refuse it, but he cannot advise as <hi>Rothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> has done, and be an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man.</note> and hee rejoiced That such a <hi>Discoverer of Thieves,</hi> was of his mind, as <hi>wise a man as himselfe:</hi> But I did assure him upon that assurance he gave to mee, That <hi>Rotherham</hi> his ghostly Father, was the most notable Theefe in all the Den; he gets no answer from me; But goe you and say thus unto him. <q>A mad dog may fly at your throat, a viper may hang upon your hand, A den of Thieves (now you have discovered them) may breake into your house, Rob and spoile, and murther you and yours there; if so it fall out, you can consider, <hi>It is for your sin;</hi> God is just, you must not stave off the Dog, not shake off the Viper not resist the Robbers, tell him so.</q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed I will not, I will not <hi>exalt folly;</hi> I will not declare my selfe to bee a Foole or a Knave before all the Congregation; doubtlesse so the Person will account of me, and call me so too, if I should speake unto him in your words; That hee must give his throat to the mad dog; his hand to the Viper; open his door to the Robbers; doubtlesse he would call mee foole and a knave too, for saying so.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, the person has answered himself. Now because you have made some Discovery here of a notable Thiefe, the chiefest in all the den; Ile give you some advice; doe not hearken to such fellowes who oppose the Covenant, reject them, and their opinion: Doe not let <hi>will</hi> rule thou, but reason, refined, and rectified by the Rule and <hi>Will</hi> of God▪ which will teach you to serve God, and His providence; to hold fast the truth, and contend for the Faith; very nature will teach you in other matters to resist the Devill, to stave off a Dog, To shake off a Viper; To drive from you those Swine, To resist Scorpions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53875:30"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am fully resolved, and it is in the purpose of my heart, (The</hi> Lord <hi>who put it there, keepe it there) To renounce my owne wisdome, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> follow no guide farther, then I can follow him with mine eye, and see clearely, That</hi> he walks by his rule. I am perswaded now that it may be said of the wisest man upon the face of the earth, that if he be his owne teacher, he has a foole to his Master.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, but before I conclude I shall command your answere to a verie grave Question, whereunto I make way thus: There are but two sides or parties in the land, <hi>The King and his partie, The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their party;</hi> A cursed division it is, and cursed are they that have divided them, though indeed, and in true construction, the King in his politicall capacitie cannot be divided from his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament: But we see the <hi>rent,</hi> and so it seemes to be now, and these two sides and parties stand with swords pointed each at other; This is the Question now, <hi>Who shall have the day or victory?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alas, why doe you aske me such a question, I cannot tell what to think; this</hi> I <hi>know,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ella geti nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los placuit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitura trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <hi>who ever shall have the victorie, neither shall have the triumph.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You are mistaken now, that side which has the victorie shall have great cause of triumph too (in the Lord): but answere my question, Which side shall have the victorie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Indeed I cannot tell;</hi> I <hi>can tell that the Parliaments sword stands p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted against Dogges, Swine, and Scorpions; but</hi> I <hi>consider the</hi> strength <hi>that Dogges have, especially when they are mad; and what tumults Swinish men make when they are drunk with rage;</hi> I <hi>perceive what is the force and fraud of Serpents;</hi> I <hi>consider also withall, how they multiply upon us like fishes: these Dogges, and Swine, and Scorpions, are scattered through every quarter of the land, and yet conjoyned and</hi> folded like thornes <hi>together, and all to make the house of</hi> Esau <hi>a</hi> flame, <hi>and the</hi> house of Jacob as stubble: <hi>Therefore in my eye the Parliament and their side are small, and (in my apprehension) their case was more hopefull two yeares agoe then now: Then</hi> I <hi>thought God would end the warre quickly, He would thrust-downe his ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>es, and lift-up his friends suddenly: But now when we seeme to set our faces beaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and to come-up to Gods termes, He seemes to goe backe, the breach seemes to be made wider, and the Scale turnes in sight to the Kings side; for all the</hi> Irish — <hi>and the Divels with them, are laid upon the Scale to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance the Scots. Indeed I see little hope, Friends are few, and enemies are many, and increase every day: hear you not what droves and heards of Beasts (of prey) break-in; I say not well</hi> (break-in) <hi>are called-in, and answere their call every day? And our brethren the Scots, our</hi> strong arme <hi>whereon we leane, these are not come: Come they will, that is sure, for however they are blasphemed, none so faithfull to God and his cause as are they: but they will come too late sure, all will be lost first. And so</hi> I <hi>have formed, and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53875:30"/> my thought unto you, but your judgement is more cleared in these matters, pray you what thinke you?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You shall heare, not what I thinke, but what I know; but I must chide you first, and my selfe more hearilie: How doe we walke man! by sight, and so wee speake what lieth uppermost: we say</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That dogges, and swine, and scorpions, are scattered through the whole land, and yet are <hi>folded together</hi> like thornes, to doe mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. No strange thing, the Church has ever been as sheep among wolves, yet not devoured; and so the right hand of the Lord has been magnified in their preservation.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) See our selves speake, adversaries we say are strong, friends weake: indeed we speake as fooles speake, and falslie; the contrarie is true; The adversaries are weake, and Gods friends are strong: It is a resolved case, <hi>They are weake as water, as a Doe without a heart, who have provoked God,</hi> though in sight as strong as <hi>Goliah,</hi> and as completelie armed as was hee <hi>Cap a pe,</hi> as wee say, from head to foot.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) Observe how wise we are! we thought God would have ended the warre quickly: Who bad us thinke so? we have beene warring against God, vve have vvalked contrarie to Him all our yeares, and vve thought He vvould vvalke contrarie to us but one yeare. We thought the Lord would but suffer the fire of His wrath to kindle upon us, and no more, Hee would put it out presently: Who bad us thinke so? Not the Lord, nor His Word, nor His Servants, that speake as the Oracles of God; for is our <hi>drosse</hi> and our <hi>scum</hi> so small, that a small fire of short continuance wil serve the turne! We have been breaking His Law these (I know not how) many yeares; vve thought the Lord would make a breach upon us onely, and make it up presentlie: We are fooles for thinking so. we have been grieving His Spirit (by our lying vanities) I know not how long, yet we thought the Lord would grieve our Spirits a moneth, and no longer, He would comfort us the next moneth. we tooke away the Day of His <hi>Rest,</hi> we profaned that Day, never people did as we did; yet we thought the Lord would make us <hi>Restlesse,</hi> He would disquiet us but a verie little while: Surely these are vaine thoughts.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) See how ignorantlie we speake; God goes backe! God does not goe backe vve goe backe; vve change, there is no change in God; vvhat He did last yeare, and this yeare, are the same He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to doe before the vvorlds were in being: We goe backe, God goes forward, and carries on His worke like a God in all His peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples sight.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:53875:31"/>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Say you so! But I told you the breach seemes wider; There is a firme union betwixt the King and the — Irish; and you know what followes, our burthens are like to be encreased.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>If we poore ones could hearken, (but we cannot for <hi>anguish of spirit and cruell bondage</hi>) if we could observe, here were the best signe that ever vvas beheld since Israel vvas in Egypt; for as then, when the Task-masters rage encreased, brickes and burdens vvere multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>Moses</hi> came; so it will be now, vvhen the Irish are called-in, now God is called-in; they hasten, and God hastens, (what to do?) To get Himselfe a Name, and an honour, as then, so now, over this —Egyptian host, them and their King: It is so, but our eyes are closed, our hearts shut up, therefore are wee so mistaken and so dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heartned. The Lord Christ prophesied of these verie times, when <hi>Kingdome shall rise against Kingdome,</hi> when <hi>His people shall be hated of all for His names sake,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.10.17.</note> when <hi>the dayes of vengeance will come.</hi> Let me aske this question; <hi>What doe we now?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile tell you what I doe, let others answere for themselves: I doe nothing but sit still and complaine of the Rebels.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You doe not answere me to my minde, and so you put me to the trouble of another question, upon this supposition; Your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour lets loose his <hi>masti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e-dog</hi> upon you, the dog does like a dogge, flies at your face, and bites off your nose, you complaine now, of vvhom? that is the question.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of my neighbour, upon just reason.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You say vvell; and for the verie same reason should you complaine of your selfe, and your owne rebellions; for your rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions have called these Rebells in, and given them power over you. But to my former question, you see the times the same that vvere prophesied-of, my question is, What is your posture now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My heart failes me for feare, my countenance is cast downe, I am in no good posture of defence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed I thought so; I see my owne posture, and the posture of the Nation in yours; most contrarie all this to what should be, and to vvhat the Lord chargeth us to doe. Our countenance is cast downe, vve are charged <hi>to looke up;</hi> our head hangs down <hi>like a bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rush,</hi> the Lord commands, saying, <hi>Lift up your heads.</hi> We expect now destruction upon destruction, the Lord Christ bids us expect now deliverance upon deliverance, for great troubles evermore have ushered them in. See (I pray you) this is the good vvord of the Lord, <hi>When these things come to passe, then look-up, and lift up your heads, for your redemption drawes nigh.</hi> See again, how good the Lords words are, and how contrarie our hearts and their <hi>posture</hi> are unto them, for</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:53875:31"/>(5.) We say the Scorpions come flying-in upon us, here they are, and there they are, like an Adder in everie path; and now the Parliament (I meane still all the faithfull in the Land) shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroied: Fooles! nay vvorse then Fooles, vve are right <hi>Barbarians,</hi> no better; for our thoughts are as theirs vvere;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 28.6.</note> The Scorpion <hi>fastned</hi> on <hi>Pauls</hi> hand; the standers-by savv that, and they looked when <hi>Paul should have swollen, or fallen downe dead suddenly:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vers.</hi> 6.</note> These vvere Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; And vvhat are vve? We see these Scorpions fastened upon the Parliaments hand; now the Parliament shall be destroied, thinke vve; our thoughts shew vvhat vve are; the Parliament shall doe now as <hi>Paul</hi> did then, they shall <hi>shake these venemous beasts off their hands into the fire, and they shall feele no harme.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe you thinke so?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I said I vvould tell you, not vvhat I think, but vvhat I know: I know it shall be so, as sure as the <hi>Lord</hi> our God is <hi>Lord</hi> over the Lords of the vvorld; so sure as the <hi>King of Saints</hi> is King over the Kings of the earth, so sure. But I shall impart no more of my knowledge til we have chid our hearts more.</p>
                  <p n="6">(6.) We said, the Irish come in apace, and our hearts mis-give us: We must chide our hearts, and say, it is not onely just, but good it should be so: For Gods people have contracted much filth, they are growne soule and nastie: Indeed we should welcome these Scullions (as sent to us from God) whose end is by them to <hi>scoure</hi> and <hi>whiten</hi> His Church: Amen.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.35.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">(7.) We rise and fall, as our friends stand, and our <hi>helpers</hi> come-in, as appeares by that you spoke even now concerning the Scots: I pray as heartily as I can, The Lord blesse the Scots, They have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared for the <hi>Lord</hi> alwaies, as His matters have required: Now, the same <hi>Lord</hi> appeare to them, and for them, and in them; let not any of them, that have engaged themselves in their Lords quarrell, let n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of them vvant an <hi>Advocate with the Father;</hi> They have set their affection to the cause of their God, now the Lord set his heart upon them, and everie one of them that have so done, and blesse them as He did His servant <hi>Abraham,</hi> make them and their house a blessing: Amen. But they cannot be a blessing unto us for mighty Reason.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ah Lord! not a blessing to us; why doe you say so? and what is your reason?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>I have no other reason but from your owne mouth, and that is a mightie reason: You said, that the Scots are our <hi>strong arme,</hi> and we <hi>leane</hi> upon them; then I say, they cannot be a <hi>blessing;</hi> wee may call for their hands, and use them, but we must not make them
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53875:32"/> our <hi>Arme:</hi> we must chide our hearts off this arme, and bring them up to fixe and <hi>leane</hi> on Gods Arm, if we looke to be held-up. Judge you of this matter, supposing your case, this: You lay all the bulke and waight of your bodie upon a reed, which the least puffe of wind does bend▪ will your strong supporters (your legges) doe you any service now? you know they cannot. It is so, if we make flesh our arme, if we leane thereon, the <hi>everlasting Armes</hi> withdraw themselves from <hi>unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>neath;</hi> and they must fall, vvho have not underneath the <hi>everlasting Armes.</hi> But vvhat weake hearts have we, because still lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on the armes of flesh, therefore how floating up and downe, as the ebbing and flowing waters! If the arme of flesh be strong we are strong; if that be weake, vve faint: The Lord help us and sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish our hearts, Amen, that He may bee our Arme vvhereon to leane; and then bring-in our brethren▪ as upon Eagles wings. Amen.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. We said in our haste, <hi>Help will come too late:</hi> Wee must chide our hearts for saying so; Help never came too late unto the Church, it comes ever in the fittest time, in season.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>But (Sir) though you will not tell me your thoughts Ile tell you mine, such as feares and terrours round-about have shaped them; these are my thoughts: That if the Lord does not deliver us this yeare, vve shall be all destroied next yeare; the sword must eat us up or the famine: It must be so, there is little hope it can be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed you must be chid <hi>It will be so,</hi> and, <hi>It must be so:</hi> How doe you know the thoughts of the Lord? I doe assure you, that in the very same yeare which starre-gazers thought vvould prove the most seasonable yeare to the vvorld, the floud came, and swept the vvorld away. I confesse we may make shreud and sad conjectures, and just cause there is of feare, when we looke into our selves, and abroad into the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>So say I too; I judge of vvhat will be no further then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ason and sense assures me: The robbers are in everie field, and so mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous they are, they take away whole <hi>Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mes</hi> at once, and what they cannot consume they spoile: The husband-man cannot sow, then I am sure he cannot reap; there must be a famine next yeare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly you should bee dealt sharply withall; can you tell what <hi>encrease</hi> the Lord may give to those places, where these Robbers, spoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, mischievous villaines, have not come? I pray you consider, The servants of the Lord are now helping their Lord against those <hi>mighty hunters</hi> to thrust them forth of the Land, and to take the <hi>prey</hi> out of their hand; an acceptable work, is it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes, but i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is impossible.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:53875:32"/>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Now ile chide sure: dare you say that is impossible to be done, which the Lord does every day, according to his good Word unto his people? <hi>The Captives of the mighty men, shall bee taken away,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Esa.</hi> 49.25, 26.</note>
                     <hi>and the prey of the terrible shall be delivered,</hi> for, and so forth; looke you there, consider on it, and you will speak no more as a fool speaketh. Answer you my Question now▪ This helping the Lord against the mighty Adversaries of the Lord is it an acceptable worke to the Lord, or is it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I must needs answer, it is an acceptable worke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, another question; The Servants of the Lord have, by <hi>raying in prayer,</hi> gained one <hi>Lip</hi> and <hi>Shoulder,</hi> they are now <hi>intent,</hi> and in a ready frame of spirit towards this great worke; The finding out of the <hi>right way of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ds Worship;</hi> The clearing the VVorship of God from the Bishops blasphemies; and <hi>setling</hi> Religion. What think you, Is this worke according to the <hi>will</hi> and Command of God, and to the heart of his people, is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes doubtlesse, the Servants of the Lord cannot be better employed for their Lord, then in this worke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>You say well; And if your servants lay out themselves for you, in the faithfull discharge of their care and trustt; and in an Answerablenesse to all your lawfull commands, you will provide for these Servants, and protect them too, if it bee in your power will you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yes sure, you need make no doubt of that.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor need you make any doubt, but God will provide for you and protect you, if you bee his faithfull servant, engaged upon his worke, if you lay your selfe-out for him, all you have, and all you are (for all is from him) if you lay-out all for him, He will provide for you sure enough; you are carelesse and secure at that point, a e you not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>B.</speaker>
                  <p>No indeed! why then you doe thinke, that God will not do (you cannot question His power) for his faithfull servants, as you would doe for yours. I pray you thinke againe, and you will thinke more wisely. I wil advise you now, and tell you what I know presently; let not <hi>your heart</hi> bee troubled, chide distrustfull thoughts about the <hi>Famine</hi> and the <hi>Sword;</hi> be assured, <hi>that faith feares not a Famine,</hi> it laughs at the Sword;<note place="margin">Fides famem non timet. <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.</note> it is not <hi>afraid of the beasts of the Earth:</hi> doe your worke, lay out your selfe wholly for God and His Cause; doe your worke so, as to adorne your name, and the Gospel, and your profession; doe it so, and bee no longer sad, nor troubled about the <hi>burt</hi> the Adversary will doe to us, this or the next yeare
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53875:33"/> Bee assured, God will doe us good; we serve a good Master; wee have a gracious, a glorious <hi>King</hi> in Heaven. And so I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e tell you what I know; for I know the word of God is true. This is the word of the Lord; My <hi>Servants shall eate, but yee</hi> (the <hi>Lord</hi> speakes to Dogs, and Swine, and Scorpions, Robbers, Murtherers,) <q>but yee shall be hungry; My Servants shall drinke, but you shall be thirsty; My Servants shall rejoice, but you shall be ashamed:</q> My servants shall sing for joy of heart,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Esa.</hi> 67.13.14 15.</note> but you shall cry for sorrow of heart, and you shall leave your name for a curse unto my Chosen, sayes the Lord. And so we will conclude against the Adversaries, and for the friends and servants of the Lord,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.12, 13, 14, 15.</note>
                     <hi>The Lord shall disappoint the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the crafty, so that their hands cannot performe their enterprise, &amp;c.</hi> and so on to the 15 verse: <hi>But he saveth the poore from the sword, from their mouth, and from the hand of the mighty.</hi> There is more yet, they are pronounced happy, who are vexed with briars, and grieved with thornes, and corrected (it is but a correction) with scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vers.</hi> 17.</note> for the same Lord who <hi>made His people sore, will bind them up;</hi> and <hi>He that wounded them with one hand, will make whole with both hands,</hi> Yet this is not all,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vers.</hi> 11.</note>
                     <hi>The Lord will set on high those which be low, that those which mourne may be exalted:</hi> How high? to the highest exaltation that is imaginable,<note place="margin">It is the same word with that, <hi>Psal.</hi> 3 2. which wee translate <hi>help.</hi> This word signifies <hi>safety</hi> here amidst Wolves; That word in the Psalm, has a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table increase of a letter and vowells, which implies a double salvation here and hereafter; The great Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Godly.</note> * <hi>exalted to safety.</hi> Looke you there, what can the dogges, and swine, and scorpions, doe against these servants of the <hi>Lord?</hi> Their <hi>Tongue,</hi> their <hi>Feet,</hi> and their <hi>Sting,</hi> cannot reach these servants of the Lord, they are <hi>Exalted to safety.</hi> Hearken what the Lord saies once more, all ye that are fearefull in heart, and be no more fearfull nor full of care; be diligent, and do good, and bee no further troubled; Hearken: <hi>He that scattered Israel will gather him, and keep him as a shepheard doth his flocke: All they that devoure thee shall be devoured, and all thine adversaries, every one of them, shall goe into captivity; and they that spoile thee shall be a spoile; and all that prey upon thee I will give for a prey: for I will restore health unto thee, and I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ll h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>le thee of thy wounds, saith the Lord, Ier.</hi> 31.10. and 30.16, 17. Amen.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:53875:33"/>
            <head>A POSTSCRJPT.</head>
            <p>I Have much exceeded my allowance here, and yet a good portion of my undertaking is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, touching Arch-Bishops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The reason is, because the case of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> unexpectedly was cast in here, upon the face of all the faithfull in the World; <hi>Jsraels</hi> two cases also, and the practice of the primitive Christians, together with <hi>Ferns</hi> blasphemy, all this to make it our case, and to prove our practice to bee rebellious. I doe not doubt to say now, That I have cleared <hi>Israels</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and them of rebellion, our owne practice also to be now as justifiable in resisting, as was the practice of the primitive Christians in suffering▪ And <hi>Ferns</hi> blasphemy against God and the King, is set so close upon his forehead, that all the water in the Sea shall not wash it off; I have but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, That he who reades, would read it all, and in order, else nothing at all.</p>
            <p>The other portion of my undertaking, Ile give forth intire of its self, with as full, and yet as short a hand as I can. Surely if the sentence from mans law, which is but an abstract from the Law of God, and should hold a conformity thereunto, be as quick against these kind of men, as it is from
<pb facs="tcp:53875:34"/> Gods mouth, wee shall dispatch them quickly. But it is considerable, that the Bishops Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the greatest Idol in the Land, and has mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied Idolls all over the Christian world; And now the Kings of the earth doe weep over them, so doe the Merchants. Here will be a <hi>Scuffle,</hi> a pleading for them; very little will be said for the Arch-Bishops, more for the Bishops; much for the defence of some, why they should not suffer with the rest, who have offended <hi>Rome</hi> as eagerly in shew, as others have defended her indeed; much also for the continuing of the name, and of their Office: We shall argue clear against all this, find all guilty; <hi>name</hi> and <hi>thing,</hi> and all to be cast out. And all this for the honour of the (Scripture) <hi>Bishop,</hi> and for the confusion of the <hi>lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>